<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><rss xmlns:dc="http://purl.org/dc/elements/1.1/" xmlns:content="http://purl.org/rss/1.0/modules/content/" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom" version="2.0"><channel><title><![CDATA[Singulatives in West Germanic]]></title><description><![CDATA[Obsidian digital garden]]></description><link>http://github.com/dylang/node-rss</link><image><url>lib/media/favicon.png</url><title>Singulatives in West Germanic</title><link></link></image><generator>Webpage HTML Export plugin for Obsidian</generator><lastBuildDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 13:23:02 GMT</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="lib/rss.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml"/><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 13:22:40 GMT</pubDate><copyright><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></copyright><ttl>60</ttl><dc:creator>Matilda Carbo</dc:creator><item><title><![CDATA[Singulatives in West Germanic]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><img alt="HY logo placeholder.png" src="lib/media/hy-logo-placeholder.png"><br><br>Linguistic Diversity and Digital Humanities - General linguistics<br>
Master's thesis]]></description><link>draft/0.-introduction/0.1-cover.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/0. Introduction/0.1 Cover.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 13:05:34 GMT</pubDate><enclosure url="lib/media/hy-logo-placeholder.png" length="0" type="image/png"/><content:encoded>&lt;figure&gt;&lt;img src=&quot;lib/media/hy-logo-placeholder.png&quot;&gt;&lt;/figure&gt;</content:encoded></item><item><title><![CDATA[0.2 Front matter]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Faculty: Faculty of Arts<br>
Degree programme: Linguistic Diversity and Digital Humanities<br>
Study track: General linguistics<br>
Author: Matilda Carbo<br>
Title: Singulatives in West Germanic<br>
Level:<br>
Month and year: XX 2025<br>
Number of pages:<br>
Keywords: singulatives, West Germanic, Afrikaans, Dutch, Frisian, German, Scots, Yiddish, typology<br>
Supervisor or supervisors: Silva Nurmio<br>
Where deposited:<br>
Additional information:<br>Abstract:]]></description><link>draft/0.-introduction/0.2-front-matter.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/0. Introduction/0.2 Front matter.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 08:31:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[0.3 Table of contents (= Outline)]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>]]></description><link>draft/0.-introduction/0.3-table-of-contents-(=-outline).html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/0. Introduction/0.3 Table of contents (= Outline).md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 13:00:12 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[0.4 Introduction]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>This work presents my research on singulatives in a set of&nbsp;West Germanic (&lt; Indo-European) languages: Afrikaans, Dutch, Frisian, German, Scots, and Yiddish.<br>Singulatives are noun forms that mean "one (unit of) X", and are derived from a non-unit denoting base (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nurmio 2023.pdf > page=3" data-href="Nurmio 2023.pdf#page=3" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nurmio-2023.pdf#page=3" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nurmio 2023: 2</a>). Prior literature suggests that some West Germanic languages have singulatives.<br><br><br>(Adapted from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf > page=55" data-href="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf#page=55" href="draft/7.-references/literature/broekhuis-keizer-2012-vol-1.pdf#page=55" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1, p.33</a>)<br>However, no comprehensive study of singulatives in West Germanic exists to date. My project fills this gap: I investigate all West Germanic languages for which I could find corpora and consultants.<br>This research is a micro-typological study that aims to contribute to the macro-typology of singulatives, and to the grammatical description of all languages surveyed. <br>(comment: todo much later)<br>
Add sentence or paragraph about results, significance)<br>Chapter 1 is a survey of background literature. <br>
Chapter 2 details the research plan: research questions, materials used, and methods.<br>
Chapter 3 and 4 present the data and analysis. Chapter 3 tackles diminutives, whereas chapter 4 addresses gender alternations. Both chapters cover each language surveyed individually, before moving on to micro-typology.<br>
Chapter 5 situates my findings in macro-typology.<br>
Chapter 6 concludes the work.<br>References are given in chapter 7, in the forms of a bibliography and, unusually, the near-full set of files consulted.<br>
The last chapter contains appendices. ]]></description><link>draft/0.-introduction/0.4-introduction.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/0. Introduction/0.4 Introduction.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:38:00 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[0.5 Gloss reference]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>]]></description><link>draft/0.-introduction/0.5-gloss-reference.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/0. Introduction/0.5 Gloss reference.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 09:23:16 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1. Background literature]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The chapter begins with a presentation of literature that pertains to singulatives. This section covers both theory that informs my research, and what is known about singulatives' typology.<br>Then, we move on to the definition and sampling of West Germanic languages. <br>The chapter closes with a survey of singulatives in each language under investigation. The last section covers languages in which I proceeded with research, and those I considered but eventually excluded (English, and Scots).]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.-background-literature.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1. Background literature.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 10:50:11 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1 Singulatives in prior literature]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>This section discusses prior literature on singulatives. I begin with the origins of the term, before moving on to the definition.<br>The next subsections go over related concepts and properties of singulatives: (their place in) derivational and inflectional domains; countability; individuation; overlap with the diminutive, and finally, overlap with grammatical gender.<br>The section ends with a typological survey of singulatives, and a brief overview of their paths to emergence.<br>I close most of the subsections by explaining their relevance to my research.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1-singulatives-in-prior-literature.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1 Singulatives in prior literature.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 10:50:15 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.1 Origins of the term]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The first known use of "Singulative" is by Johann Caspar Zeuss, in Grammatica Celtica (1853: 299, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Acquaviva 2016.pdf > page=2" data-href="Acquaviva 2016.pdf#page=2" href="draft/7.-references/literature/acquaviva-2016.pdf#page=2" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Acquaviva 2016: 1172</a>), a publication that establishes Celtic languages as a branch in the Indo-European family.<br>Zeuss used "singulative" to refer to singular forms derived from bare plurals in the Brittonic branch of Celtic languages. In opposition to this term, he used "collectives" to refer to the bare plurals (Zeuss 1853: 299-301, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nurmio 2023.pdf > page=4" data-href="Nurmio 2023.pdf#page=4" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nurmio-2023.pdf#page=4" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nurmio 2023: 3</a>). Here are some examples of singulative-collective oppositions in Brittonic.<br><br><br>(Adapted from: (1) <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Stolz 2001.pdf > page=6" data-href="Stolz 2001.pdf#page=6" href="draft/7.-references/literature/stolz-2001.pdf#page=6" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Stolz 2001: 57</a>, (2) <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Bock &amp; Bruch 2008.pdf > page=59" data-href="Bock &amp; Bruch 2008.pdf#page=59" href="draft/7.-references/literature/bock-&amp;-bruch-2008.pdf#page=59" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Bock &amp; Bruch 2008: 53</a>, (3) <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jouitteau &amp; Rezac 2015.pdf > page=6" data-href="Jouitteau &amp; Rezac 2015.pdf#page=6" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jouitteau-&amp;-rezac-2015.pdf#page=6" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jouitteau &amp; Rezac 2015: 5</a>)<br>"Singulative" went on to be commonly used in Celtic linguistics, and eventually in works on other language families such as Cushitic (see <a data-href="1.1.8 Typology" href="draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.8-typology.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">1.1.8 Typology</a>). However, the definitions for "singulative" and "collective" vary between publications, and they are sometimes left implicit.<br>In recent years, "singulative" has started to be used as a comparative concept (Haspelmath 2018), as can be seen in <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Acquaviva 2016.pdf" data-href="Acquaviva 2016.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/acquaviva-2016.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Acquaviva 2016</a> and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nurmio 2023.pdf" data-href="Nurmio 2023.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nurmio-2023.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nurmio 2023</a>. The term is now used with a definition that has more cross-linguistic applicability and precision.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.1-origins-of-the-term.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.1 Origins of the term.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:38:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.2 Definition]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>(comment)<br>
Will need to signpost/quickly define "grammaticalization"/"grammaticalized" here (/also mention reanalysis)<br>In this work, I adopt the following definition of "singulative":<br>
A singulative is a derived noun form which is formed by adding a marker to a non-unit-denoting base and which denotes ‘a/one X’ or ‘a/one unit of X’.<br>
(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nurmio 2023.pdf > page=3" data-href="Nurmio 2023.pdf#page=3" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nurmio-2023.pdf#page=3" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nurmio 2023: 2</a>)
<br>In other words, the requirements for a word form to qualify as singulative are both semantic and morphological. The base word refers to a mass or plurality of something, and with the addition of a marker, it refers to one thing/being, or a unit of the same group.<br>(comment: 'the same group')<br>
SN: Let’s talk about this wording, there’s some possibility to split hairs over e.g. Welsh dillad ’clothes’, dilled-yn ’piece of clothing’<br>
MC: now rephrased but might need to think &amp; write about pseudo-collectives (heterogeneous units) somewhere<br>The resulting word form is a "singulative".<br>The marker used to derive the word form can also be called "singulative", if it fits certain conditions. I return to this point later.<br>
In this work, I frequently speak of markers rather than morphemes, because the term marker is more inclusive. This greater inclusivity reflects how diverse singulatives are, cross-typologically: singulatives are by definition marked, but not always with a discretely identifiable morpheme. (See <a data-href="1.1.8 Typology#Types of singulative markers" href="draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.8-typology.html#Types_of_singulative_markers" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">1.1.8 Typology &gt; Types of singulative markers</a>.)<br>Nurmio's definition captures similar&nbsp;morphological and semantic criteria as other comparative definitions given in typological articles, such as the following:<br>
Singulatives, then, are not just unit nouns, but unit nouns whose singular form is derived from a non-singular form by morphology with this specific function.<br>
(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Acquaviva 2016.pdf > page=2" data-href="Acquaviva 2016.pdf#page=2" href="draft/7.-references/literature/acquaviva-2016.pdf#page=2" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Acquaviva 2016: 1172</a>)
<br>(comment: same/only function)<br>
SN: Is this problematic vis-a-vis diminutive/SGT and gender/SGT markers?<br>
MC: I don't think so, but I need a paragraph touching on that. Needs to integrate: lumper v splitter, more thought re: grammaticalization<br>
A singulative/basic pair is a pair of noun forms where one member is a marked uniplex nominal (e.g., Welsh moron-en ‘carrot’), while the other member is an unmarked multiplex nominal (e.g., Welsh moron ‘carrots’).<br>
(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017.pdf > page=5" data-href="Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017.pdf#page=5" href="draft/7.-references/literature/haspelmath-&amp;-karjus-2017.pdf#page=5" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017: 1216-1217</a>)
<br>Thus, the definition I adopt simply follows publications that approach singulative as a comparative concept.<br>However, some complexity arises from drawing a distinction between singulative word forms, and singulative markers.<br>&nbsp;When we go from a mass-denoting word to a unit-denoting one through the addition of morphological material, the derived form qualifies as singulative. But the responsible marker is not necessarily singulative. It counts as a singulative marker, if its function of expressing units is grammaticalized.<br>(comment: edit)<br>
paragraph above relates to stage II; clarify/develop once I've written more about grammaticalization<br>On the other hand, a marker with a different primary function and occasional uses to express units is not a true singulative. The issue in the latter case is not the presence of another grammatical function, but rather insufficient grammaticalization.<br>To illustrate the matter, we will look at two markers from Russian (&gt; Indo-European), -k and -in, as analysed by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio (2024)</a>.<br>(comment: intro metatext)<br>
Rewrite so that it's a good intro to the argument walkthrough: two potential DIM/SGV markers. quick definition of diminutive + signpost to my longer discussion<br>Words derived with -k in Russian can refer to units:<br>
<br><br>(Adapted from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf > page=10" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf#page=10" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf#page=10" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024: 74</a>)<br>Examples X (a-c) are singulative word forms; they give the impression that -k might be a singulative morpheme.<br>
Kagan &amp; Nurmio argue that the marker -k is not a true singulative, and rather a diminutive (with singulative uses). Adding -k does not systematically lead to a mass-to-count shift: it can take count nouns and return count nouns, as well as take mass nouns and return mass nouns (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf > page=10" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf#page=10" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf#page=10" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024: 74-75</a>). <br>In addition, word forms derived with -k can lack the unit/mass contrast that would make them qualify as singulative, and they can just carry the denotation and/or connotation of a diminutive, as in example X (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf > page=11" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf#page=11" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf#page=11" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024: 75</a>). <br><br>Both of these properties run against the expectations for a grammaticalized, true singulative marker. Thus, -k is not a singulative marker, even though we observe singulative word forms that are derived with it.<br>comment: regularity of units<br>
develop this paragraph idea, connect it to grammaticalization:<br>
Another argument against viewing -k as a singulative, is the unpredictability of the unit expressed. A grammaticalized singulative would express a predictable unit, such as a natural unit ('a single X'; 'a piece of X'; 'a unit of X';...) or a packaged unit ('portion of X', 'serving of X',...); if there is variation, it is patterned. With -k, the unit expressed lacks a pattern, because some derived nouns are more lexicalized than others, so it fails in this regard.<br>
I propose this additional criterion building on Acquaviva 2016: 1174's statement that "what characterizes singulatives as a local regularity, rather than a list of irregularities, is the systematic match of a uniform exponent with a constant interpretation.")<br>Unlike -k, Russian -in is a true singulative marker.<br>
<br><br>(Adapted from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf > page=7" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf#page=7" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf#page=7" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024: 71</a>)<br>-in appears on words that refer to units that are not necesarily small, unlike -k. It always triggers a mass-to-count shift, and it does not carry the connotations associated with diminutives (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf > page=7" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf#page=7" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf#page=7" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024: 71-72</a>). These properties are consistent with grammaticalization <br>(comment: grammaticalization)<br>
More sources. Heine 2003 + ...?<br>Thus, the marker -in is a true singulative morpheme, and the words derived with it are singulative word forms.<br>My initial hypothesis is that, much like Russian, West Germanic languages have singulative word forms derived with true singulative markers, and singulative word forms derived with markers that don't qualify as true singulatives.<br>
Teasing the two apart is an objective of my research.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.2-definition.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.2 Definition.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:41:19 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.3 Derivational and inflectional domains]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Singulatives may fall in the domain of derivation, or inflection. I illustrate this with examples from languages in which it is respectively inflectional, derivational, and in a grey area between the two. In addition, I show some interaction between singulatives' domain, and grammatical number.<br>In Kambaata (&lt; Afro-Asiatic) (4), the singular form of 'cat' and 'ficus' are marked, relative to the plural counterparts. The singulative forms are the canonical singular forms of some words, and they fall under number inflection.<br>comment re: Kambaata<br>
SN: Contra Maarten Mous on Cushitic? Does Treis comment on this? You could problematise and reference this issue more, I think it is discussed in the lit (Mous at least)<br>
-&gt; consult Mous 2012<br>
-&gt;&nbsp;consult Treis 2014<br>On the other hand, in North Saami (&lt; Uralic) (5), words with -čalbmi are not the singular form of the base they derive from, but rather distinct words that refer to units of the base. Singulatives formed with -čalbmi have singular and plural forms, which supports the idea that they are the result of derivation.<br><br><br>(Adapted from (X) <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Treis 2012.pdf > page=3" data-href="Treis 2012.pdf#page=3" href="draft/7.-references/literature/treis-2012.pdf#page=3" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Treis 2012: 3</a>; (X) <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Ylikoski 2022.pdf > page=1" data-href="Ylikoski 2022.pdf#page=1" href="draft/7.-references/literature/ylikoski-2022.pdf#page=1" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Ylikoski 2022: 1</a>, 3, 7) <br>On the other hand, singulative Arabic (&gt; Afro-Asiatic) -a(t) falls in a grey area between inflection and derivation.<br>When used as a singulative, -a(t) seems derivational, because adding it to a base does not create the singular counterpart of the base. The base is a grammatical singular referring to a plurality, and pluralized singulatives occur, much like in North Saami (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic.pdf > page=24" data-href="Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic.pdf#page=24" href="draft/7.-references/literature/dali-mathieu-2021-arabic.pdf#page=24" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic: 24</a>).<br><br><br>(Adapted from Dali &amp; Mathieu 2021: 24) <br>(comment: find other example)<br>
find better example than 'cattle', sth like 'bee', 'goat'... will need different source<br>However, this description corresponds to what is prescribed in Standard Arabic (Dhifallah 2022). In contrast, in Tunisian Arabic,&nbsp;the agreement pattern of the collective base is variable: plural agreement is acceptable with some collective words, which is similar to the behavior of inflectional collective/singulative pairs. <br>(comment: more sources/nuance w Arabic, Maltese, re: derivation/inflection)<br>
Silva's comments:<br>
Maltese: Corbett 2001<br>
Dali &amp; Mathieu (what do they say about DER/INFL?)<br>
General note, adding more references incl. some comparative ones like this is a good idea when possible<br>
Arabic &amp; agreement: read about Maltese --&gt; will need a note clarifying status of Maltese/Arabic<br>
...<br>
Own thoughts:<br>
Need to find other sources to confirm that this applies to COLL/SGVE like ants, dates, etc.<br>
Add example<br>The blurring between the domains has to do with the fact that singulative -a(t) emerged through morphological reanalysis, and carries multiple grammatical functions, some derivational (such as nominalisation), and some inflectional (marking the feminine) (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic.pdf > page=4" data-href="Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic.pdf#page=4" href="draft/7.-references/literature/dali-mathieu-2021-arabic.pdf#page=4" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic: 4</a>, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Acquaviva &amp; Daniel 2022.pdf > page=145" data-href="Acquaviva &amp; Daniel 2022.pdf#page=145" href="draft/7.-references/literature/edited-volumes/acquaviva-&amp;-daniel-2022.pdf#page=145" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Fehri 2022: 134</a>).<br>(comment: Fehri)<br>
more pages from Fehri 2022 would be better<br>In summary, singulatives may fall under derivation or inflection. Surveying singulatives is any given language requires investigation in both domains. Studying singulatives' interaction with grammatical number assists in establishing which domain they belong to.<br><br>
<br>
<br>The parentheses indicate an optional morpheme: without -ta, the form is masculine, and with -ta, it is feminine (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Treis 2012.pdf > page=3" data-href="Treis 2012.pdf#page=3" href="draft/7.-references/literature/treis-2012.pdf#page=3" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Treis 2012: 3</a>).<a href="about:blank#fnref-1-b91ba2b1ff6401ee" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.3-derivational-and-inflectional-domains.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.3 Derivational and inflectional domains.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:41:49 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.4 Countability]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Next, I address countability and its relation to singulatives, beginning with a discussion of the terms: mass noun, non-count noun, count noun.<br>As explained by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf > page=17" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf#page=17" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf#page=17" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grimm (2012: 3)</a>, "mass nouns" is an ambiguously used term. Depending on the author, it may refer to a grammatical category defined by its distribution (e.g. words that can be used with 'much', not 'many' in English), or a semantic group (mass-like referents such as substances ), irrespective of their grammatical behavior.<br>Like <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf > page=17" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf#page=17" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf#page=17" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grimm (2012: 3)</a>, I set aside the term 'mass noun' due to its ambiguity, and rather speak of count nouns, and non-count nouns. These terms group nouns according to their distributional properties, not their meaning.<br>The contrast can be illustrated by showing that some words are usually grammatical with "many", or numbers, and ungrammatical with "much"... whereas the opposite applies to another set of words.&nbsp;The first are described as count nouns, and the latter, non-count.<br>(comment: English bias - nuance text, find sources)<br>
SN: Note that these are tests for English; longer discussion in our SLE workshop abstract. You need a somewhat clearer distinction between what's typological here and what's English (English being used as an example?). Also more references, comparison..<br>
MC: So edit to bring out more strongly contrast between typological tests VS english tests — mention that gram tests may transfer well to West Germ lg. + transfer may be poor in other languages, need studies on countability in more diverse lg. Find lit on this!!<br>
-&gt; Kwak 2014<br>
-&gt;&nbsp;Chierchia 2014: 147-? from Li et al 2014<br>
maybe also -&gt; Cheng 2012, from edited volume Massam 2012<br>
-&gt; other chapters from Massam 2012, which?<br><br>
X. a) Many cats, b) 3 cats, c) ?*much cat(s) -&gt; 'cat' is count<br>X. a) ?Many snow(s), b)  3 snows, c) much snow -&gt; 'snow' is non-count<br>(own examples)<br>A superficial understanding of count and non-count nouns gives the impression that the two are binary, mutually exclusive categories, but closer study quickly reveals that this view is untenable.<br>There are several distributional tests for categorizing count, and non-count nouns, and, as <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf > page=18" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf#page=18" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf#page=18" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grimm (2012: 4)</a> explains, " not all nouns which could be classified as countable or non-countable by some distributional properties behave identically with respect to all of the distributional properties. Another source of complication is that nouns often have several uses, some countable and some not."<br>With this view, nouns have more or less tendency to behave as count, or non-count, and a clear picture of their status emerges by testing them in different contexts (both grammatical and semantic). In the words of Grimm (2012: 11)&nbsp; "countability is a matter of degree and [...] different nouns have different countability "preferences"."<br>(comment: source countability)<br>
SN: For this, citing Allan’s work is a must (Nouns and countability)<br>
-&gt;&nbsp;Allan 1980<br>If we revisit the basic examples given in XX, we might conclude that: 'cat' has a high count preference, and in rare contexts, it can behave as a non-count noun.<br>X. Grinding context: "there is much cat on the road" (...understood as 'much cat matter')<br>(comment: universal grinder)<br>
Write more. Find other source, not just Grimm<br>
-&gt;&nbsp;Rothstein 2017 p.180-?<br>
-&gt;&nbsp;Kwak 2014<br>On the other hand, 'snow' has a high non-count preference, but in rare contexts, it can present as count.<br>X. Packaged context: "there are many snows in the tundra" (understood as 'many types of snow')<br>(comment: universal packager)<br>
Write more. Find other source, not just Grimm)<br>
-&gt;&nbsp;Rothstein 2017 p.180-<br>
-&gt;&nbsp;Kwak 2014<br>Let's now turn to singulatives.<br>First, when singulative are described as selecting bases that are "mass", it must be understood in semantic terms. (See <a data-href="1.1.5 Individuation" href="draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.5-individuation.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">1.1.5 Individuation</a> for more on this topic.)<br>Second, singulatives interact with grammatical countability. A singulative word form largely behaves as a count noun, since it refers to an individuated referent.<br>In some languages, singulative markers target bases that tend to be non-count, and turns them into count nouns. A consistent shift from non-count to count indicates a 'true' singulative per <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf > page=7" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf#page=7" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf#page=7" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio (2024: 73)</a>).<br>comment: obligatoritification?<br>
connect to grammaticalization - obligatorification?<br>On the other hand, it is also possible for singulative markers to take bases that are count, and return a derived form that is also count. <br>comment: add Arabic + Brittonic examples<br>However, a non-count word form, or marker that derives non-count forms, cannot be called singulatives, because the un-individuated meaning is incompatible with the individuating function of singulatives. Accordingly, if a marker occasionally derives non-count nouns, it is unlikely to be a true singulative, as in the case of Russian -k.<br>(comment: nuance this)<br>
connected to AB stage, grammaticalization<br><br>Thus, the morphosyntactic distribution of singulatives is sensitive to countability. Singulatives' bases can score high in non-count preference, or admit either count and non-count.<br>Additionally, singulative words forms must behave as count nouns by default -- meaning, in most contexts, with rare exceptions like universal grinding.<br>This information is useful for recognizing true singulatives, and is integrated in my investigation of West Germanic.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.4-countability.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.4 Countability.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:05:36 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.5 Individuation]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Singulatives are not just sensitive to morphosyntax -- they must also be defined and investigated in terms of semantics. This is where a discussion of individuation enters the picture.<br>I discuss the scale of individuation (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf > page=1" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf#page=1" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf#page=1" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grimm 2012</a>), as well as natural units and packaged units.<br>The scale of individuation is an implicational scale proposed by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf > page=67" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf#page=67" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf#page=67" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grimm 2012: 53-57</a>, to describe cross-linguistic tendencies in number markedness. The higher a referent is on the scale, the more it is likely to be marked when singular, and non-singular when unmarked. (Non-singular might mean plural, collective, or general number, depending on the language's number system.)<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf > page=87" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf#page=87" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf#page=87" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Grimm (2012: 73)</a> predicts that number markers usually target continuous portions of the scale of individuation. This is what makes the scale implicational.<br>
More concretely, it would go against his prediction for a singulative to target liquids and insects, and "ignore" granular aggregates (which sit between the liquids and insects on the scale).<br><br>(Nurmio 2023:&nbsp;3, 4-8)<br>(comment: todo more refs)<br>
SN: More refs from there, e.g. Goddard<br>Let's now turn to natural and packaged units.<br>
Natural units refer to things with fixed, stable boundaries, such as natural minimal parts (grains of sand, blades of grass) or individuals of a group or herd (a pig, an ant,...).<br>
By contrast, packaged units refer to units made of substances without natural minimal parts. Consequently, the type of unit expressed must get conventionalized. Properties needed to count as unit = shape, size,...<br>
(a cheese; a chocolate bar; a beer)<br>
<br>Some packaged units are closer to natural minimal parts than others (eg fruit jelly candy; a candy split in two may not be called a marmeladka)
<br>Similarly, some natural units are closer to packaged units than others. Regarding vegetation, "unit of X" can in theory refer to multiple parts of plants (grain, seed, fruit,...). In practice, however, singulatives in this semantic class refer to a single unit (seed and not fruit, or vice versa) -- in other words, one unit gets conventionalized as the relevant natural unit for a given plant, out of a few possible options.
<br>Let's bring everything together.<br>
Referents of bases for singulatives are predicted to sit somewhere in the low-to-middle area of the individuation scale. The addition of a singulative marker to the base makes the word refer to an individuated referent.<br>
In line with Grimm's typological predictions (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf > page=87" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf#page=87" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf#page=87" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">2012: 73</a>), I expect true singulative markers to target continuous portions of the individuation scale.<br>
But what about markers that derive singulative word forms, but are not true singulatives: do they target continuous portions of the scale? This is unclear, and each possible answer leads to different implications.<br>
<br>Yes: ....?
<br>No (as in: not necessarily): We can use non-respect of the scale as a feature of markers that are not true singulatives. Respect of the scale is a necessary, but not sufficient, condition to back the claim that a marker is a true singulative.
<br>(comment: prediction of scale)<br>
SN: Elaborate? The Germanic ones are liquids, so goes with the scale<br>
Develop more, the idea being: it can apply, but it doesn’t have to, if we’re not dealing with true SGVE. Find example. Consequence: non-compliance suggests non-sgve; supports but doesn’t garantee that it’s sgve, since non-sgve might comply too.<br>Singulative word forms can refer to natural, or packaged units.<br>
<br>Distinction -&gt; compare behavior of different semantic groups in 1 language, or micro/macro-typologically
<br>Distinction -&gt; different way to extend units
<br>The study of singulatives offers an opportunity to validate the individuation scale, and potentially add granularity to it.<br>
<br>Conventionalization of one unit / grammaticalization VS lexicalization
]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.5-individuation.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.5 Individuation.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:06:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.6 Diminutive and singulative overlap]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>In this section, I discuss the overlap between diminutives and singulatives. I begin by going over the definition of diminutive, in terms of denotation and connotation.<br>I walk through earlier reports of the singulative/diminutive overlap. I address the semantic evolution from diminutive to singulative, then conclude with the relevance of the overlap to West Germanic.<br>Diminutives refer to something small. This is the core denotation of the category, and often mentioned as the main definitional aspect of diminutives.<br>For instance, <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jurafsky 1996.pdf > page=12" data-href="Jurafsky 1996.pdf#page=12" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jurafsky-1996.pdf#page=12" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jurafsky (1996: p. 543)</a> defines diminutives as "any morphological device which means at least 'small'", and <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nieuwenhuis 1985.pdf > page=11" data-href="Nieuwenhuis 1985.pdf#page=11" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nieuwenhuis-1985.pdf#page=11" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nieuwenhuis (1985: 1)</a> states that "smallness is indeed the first meaning that springs to mind when one thinks of diminutive".<br>However, it would be a mistake to reduce diminutives to this single meaning. Diminutives frequently carry a range of connotations that may be diverse, contradictory, and making the denotation 'small' lose in salience. These connotations might express the attitude of the speaker towards a referent, or some other aspect of the speech act.<br>For example, pragmatic connotations of diminutives identified by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Galeas 2004.pdf > page=6" data-href="Galeas 2004.pdf#page=6" href="draft/7.-references/literature/galeas-2004.pdf#page=6" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Galeas (2004: 6-7)</a> are:<br>
<br>ludic (non-serious, playful tone);
<br>meiosis (polite attenuation);
<br>baby talk (speech situation centered around a target of affection -- child, lover, pet);
<br>emotive (expressing affection and various emotions);
<br>familiarity and intimacy;
<br>sympathy and empathy.
<br>The pragmatic load of diminutives is significant, considering how common it is for multiple connotations to apply in a single utterance.<br>Galeas does not give linguistic examples for these functions, but bases his claims on pre-existing crosslinguistic literature (on Viennese German and Italian), and new data from Modern Greek (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Galeas 2004.pdf > page=4" data-href="Galeas 2004.pdf#page=4" href="draft/7.-references/literature/galeas-2004.pdf#page=4" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Galeas 2004: 4</a>). Decontextualized sentences can hardly illustrate claims related to pragmatics, so linguistic data supporting these claims would need to be situated in an explicit context of utterance.<br>(comment: context-rich examples)<br>
Give 1-2 examples of my own, context-rich, English / French? <br>In addition to the previous connotations, diminutives can also carry a pejorative meaning -- expressing contempt, or disregard.<br><br><br>(Adapted from Nurmio et al forth.)<br>Thus, diminutives tend to carry a wide set of connotations emerging from pragmatic uses, and they cannot be simply defined as meaning 'small'.<br>On the other hand, if a word carries some of the connotations outlined above without ever having the denotation 'small', there is no ground to call it a diminutive anymore. It should receive a different label (such as: hypocoristic, meliorative, pejorative, baby talk,...).<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nieuwenhuis 1985.pdf > page=12" data-href="Nieuwenhuis 1985.pdf#page=12" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nieuwenhuis-1985.pdf#page=12" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Nieuwenhuis (1985: 2)</a> captures this nuance between denotation and connotation in his definition, which I adopt in this work:<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;&gt;"The term diminutive is used to refer to any system whereby the form of a word or words is changed for the purpose of referring to smallness, usually associated with an expression of endearment or contempt."<br>I turn to the matter of overlap in the expression of singulative, and diminutive.<br>The fact that this overlap exists is nothing new, as it was already observed by <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jurafsky 1996.pdf > page=24" data-href="Jurafsky 1996.pdf#page=24" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jurafsky-1996.pdf#page=24" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jurafsky (1996: 555)</a> and reported in German and Kambaata (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf > page=3" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf#page=3" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf#page=3" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024: 67</a>; <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Wiltschko 2006.pdf > page=1" data-href="Wiltschko 2006.pdf#page=1" href="draft/7.-references/literature/wiltschko-2006.pdf#page=1" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Wiltschko 2006: 1-2</a>; <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Treis 2012.pdf > page=7" data-href="Treis 2012.pdf#page=7" href="draft/7.-references/literature/treis-2012.pdf#page=7" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Treis 2012: 7</a>). Acquaviva (2016: 1177)'s overview of singulatives also mentions it, in the context of Welsh. Each of these sources gives one or more example illustrating overlap between singulative, and diminutive<br><br><br>(Adapted from: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jurafsky 1996.pdf > page=24" data-href="Jurafsky 1996.pdf#page=24" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jurafsky-1996.pdf#page=24" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jurafsky 1996: 555</a>; <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Wiltschko 2006.pdf > page=1" data-href="Wiltschko 2006.pdf#page=1" href="draft/7.-references/literature/wiltschko-2006.pdf#page=1" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Wiltschko 2006: 1-2</a>; <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Treis 2012.pdf > page=7" data-href="Treis 2012.pdf#page=7" href="draft/7.-references/literature/treis-2012.pdf#page=7" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Treis 2012: 7</a>; <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Acquaviva 2016.pdf > page=7" data-href="Acquaviva 2016.pdf#page=7" href="draft/7.-references/literature/acquaviva-2016.pdf#page=7" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Acquaviva 2016: 1177</a>)<br>The overlap between the expression of diminutive and singulative arises through the intermediate stage of expressing a part/whole relationship, such that the base refers to the whole, and the derived words refers to a part, and then a unit. (This is why some singulative word forms have occasionally been termed "partitive", as in <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jurafsky 1996.pdf > page=24" data-href="Jurafsky 1996.pdf#page=24" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jurafsky-1996.pdf#page=24" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jurafsky 1996: 555</a>.)<br>A priori, this relationship is unidirectional, going from a physical category (size) to a conceptual one (unit). This is in line with unidirectionality hypotheses developed to study semantic change (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jurafsky 1996.pdf > page=9" data-href="Jurafsky 1996.pdf#page=9" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jurafsky-1996.pdf#page=9" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jurafsky 1996: 540-544</a>).<br>(comment: grammaticalization)<br>
connect w reading about grammaticalization <br>Note that the "singulatives" in singulative/diminutive overlaps involve singulative word forms, but not necessarily always true singulative morphemes (Nurmio, Dires &amp; Carbo forth.; <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024</a>). (See discussion of this point in <a data-href="1.1.8 Typology#Distribution of overlapping diminutive/singulative" href="draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.8-typology.html#Distribution_of_overlapping_diminutive/singulative" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">1.1.8 Typology &gt; Distribution of overlapping diminutive/singulative</a>.)<br>The overlap between diminutive and singulatives is relevant to my study, because this &nbsp;overlap is reported in the literature for some West Germanic languages I study, such as in Dutch.<br><br><br>(Adapted from ([Broekhuis &amp; Keizer 2012: 33](<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf > page=55" data-href="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf#page=55" href="draft/7.-references/literature/broekhuis-keizer-2012-vol-1.pdf#page=55" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1, p.33</a>)))<br>Its existence is also supported by preliminary data I collected for an even greater number of languages in my set.<br>Thus, the starting point of my thesis, is that diminutives overlaps with singulatives in some West Germanic languages: more precisely, some suffixes that usually mean 'small' and/or carry various connotations, may be used to derive words that refer to units. Thus, these markers may or may not be true singulative markers, as my research elucidates.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.6-diminutive-and-singulative-overlap.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.6 Diminutive and singulative overlap.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:08:21 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.7 Gender and singulative overlap]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Singulative forms can be derived from morphemes whose main function is to express grammatical gender.<br>This can be seen in Arabic, where the morpheme -a(t) makes words grammatically feminine, and can derive words referring to women (X), as well as words referring to collectives (X) (Dali &amp; Mathieu 2021: 20-24).<br>(comment: collective)<br>
explain 'collective' <br><br><br>(Adapted from Badawi et al 2015: 109)<br>Feminine markers deriving words referring to units is a feature observed in several Afro-Asiatic languages (Nurmio 2023: 14); these expressions are contrasted with masculine, unmarked words that refer to collectivities or masses.<br>The singulative's tendency to be expressed through feminine morphology has already been observed for Chadic (&lt; Afro-Asiatic)&nbsp;by Acquaviva (2016: 1173).<br>The recurence of the association between singulative and feminine is supported by prior literature, and data from the unpublished singulatives database (Nurmio, Dires &amp; Carbo forth.). However, pairing between singulative and other genders are also possible. This is addressed in section XXX.<br>Jurafsky 1996: 535 reports that "both the diminutive and augmentative are closely associated with female gender". Hence it comes as no surprise that in some languages, singulatives simultaneously overlap with the diminutive and gender-marking (especially feminine).<br>Such double overlaps are attested in Arabic, and Berber (&lt; Afro-Asiatic) (Nurmio, Dires &amp; Carbo).<br><br>
(comment: add examples)<br>The study of gender/singulative overlap benefits from a look at noun classes that express singulatives. Noun classes&nbsp;and grammatical gender are both forms of noun classification. The two terms capture a spectrum, rather than discrete categories: "noun class" systems have more numerous classes and stronger semantic motivations than "gender" systems (source).<br>(comment: noun classes and gender)<br>
define Noun classes + give example<br>
-&gt; Bantu VS Romance<br>In either case, there is an association between noun class and unit/mass meaning, which can be diagnosed through concord. (...)<br>The association between unit/mass and gender is of interest to singulatives in West Germanic languages, because, as we will see later on, current literature on West Germanic languages reports some words&nbsp;whose gender changes depending on whether they express a unit, or a mass. Consider this example in Frisian, which has two grammatical genders (neuter, common):<br><br><br>(Adapted from TP Frisian Gender)<br>I refer to this pattern as gender alternation, and I investigate it as a unit-expressing strategy that may or may not be present in my sampled languages.<br><br>(comment: gender)<br>
Gender switch -- some SGVE markers switch the gender of the base (eg Romance) but is it a reach to put them on the same level as SGVE markers that express gender first and foremost eg Arabic<br>
MC: intuitively, gender/sgv overlap is a subcategory of singulatives that switch genders upon derivation, not sure how to unpack the distinction<br>
SN: How can you tell which is foremost? Unpack a bit more]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.7-gender-and-singulative-overlap.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.7 Gender and singulative overlap.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:28:03 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.1.8 Typology]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>In this section, I discuss: the distribution of singulative markers across languages of the world, and the types of markers observed.<br>After the overview, I turn to the distribution of some categories that overlap with the singulative: diminutive, and grammatical gender.<br><br>Until recently, singulatives were claimed to be a rare feature, with a limited distribution in terms of geography and language families (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017.pdf > page=6" data-href="Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017.pdf#page=6" href="draft/7.-references/literature/haspelmath-&amp;-karjus-2017.pdf#page=6" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017: 1217</a>).<br>For instance, Haspelmath &amp; Karjus (2017: 1220) describe singulatives as "attested in substantial numbers only in some Celtic languages, in varieties of Arabic (such as Maltese), in Cushitic languages, and in a few other languages spoken in northeastern Africa".<br>Dali &amp; Mathieu (2021: 18) discuss singulatives in Arabic and other varieties of Semitic (Biblical Hebrew, and Akkadian).<br>Grimm (2012: 22, 31, 36, 42) studies singulatives in four languages, all falling under one of the (sub)families reported in other publications: Welsh (Celtic), Turkana (Nilo-Saharan), Maltese (Semitic), Dagaare (Niger-Congo).<br>Acquaviva (2016) provides the widest coverage prior to Nurmio (2023). He states that singulatives are a prominent feature in Nilo-Saharan languages, Chadic languages (a branch of Afro-Asiatic, like Arabic), and the Brittonic branch of Celtic languages (Acquaviva 2016: 1173). He also reports singulatives in Russian, Dutch (Aquaviva 2016: 1172, 1175). The remainder of the languages with singulatives he presents are genetically unrelated and geographically distant -- Tariana (Arawak family; spoken in Amazonia, Brasil), Itelmen (Chukotko-Kamchatkan; Kamchatka peninsula, Russia), Burushaski (isolate; Pakistan), Swahili (Niger-Congo; much of East Africa) (Acquaviva 2016: 1173).<br>Nurmio (2023: 9; Nurmio, Dires, &amp; Carbo (forth.)) challenges the idea that singulatives are rare, and aims to show that they are far more common than previously thought. What follows is a snapshot of the distribution of singulatives, informed by the unpublished database (Nurmio, Dires &amp; Carbo forth.).<br>(comment: add examples throughout?)<br>First, some precisions about the families most known to have singulatives are in order. Singulatives are seen in Brittonic and Goidelic branches of Celtic, albeit far more on the Brittonic side (Welsh, Breton, Cornish), than Goidelic (observed in Irish Gaelic; not yet in Scottish Gaelic or Manx (Nurmio 2023: 3, 13; Nurmio, Dires &amp; Carbo (forth.)). They are observed in all subfamilies of Afro-Asiatic except Egyptian -- in other words, they are seen in Berber, Chadic, Cushitic, and Semitic.<br>Second, two geographic clusters emerge from the database. In both cases, the singulative may be an areal feature -- spread by contact across language families, in addition to transmission to daughter languages.<br>The first cluster centers in the Horn of Africa, with some extension to the North and West of Africa and Middle East. The list that follows presents language families in the area, which appear to have singulatives. (Note that the classification of languages of Africa into families is contentious; see Güldemann 2018. I rely on the classification given in Glottolog, as done in the database.)<br>
<br>Nilotic <a data-footref="1" href="about:blank#fn-1-b91ba2b1ff6401ee" class="footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">[1]</a> (with representatives in all branches: Eastern Nilotic, such as Bari; Southern Nilotic, such as Kipsigis; Western Nilotic, such as Dinka);
<br>Afro-Asiatic (all branches except Egyptian, hence: Semitic such as Arabic; Berber such as Nafusi Berber; Chadic such as Masa and Cushitic such as Oromo);
<br>Maban (with Masalit and Runga);
<br>Dajuic (with Shatt);
<br>Kadugli-Krongo (with Krongo);
<br>South Omotic (with Aari).
<br>In this area, singulatives are highly variable, and mostly seen in the inflectional domain&nbsp;as expressions of singular number. More research on languages of Chad-Ethiopia (a tentative area for which a modest case is made in Güldemann 2010: 12-13) would be needed to establish whether we can really call singulatives an areal feature: this would require demonstration that they spread across families through contact.<br>(comment: nuance/rewrite first sentence)<br>
"In this area, singulatives are highly variable, and mostly seen in the inflectional domain&nbsp;as expressions of singular number."-&gt; nuance this re: inflectional domain, after more reading/writing about Kambaata <br>The second cluster is diffused over Siberia, with some extension to Northern Europe (Lapland). We observe singulatives in:<br>
<br>Uralic (in half of the branches, which is to say: Mansic with Northern Mansi; Permian with Komi; Saami such as North Saami; Samoyedic such as Forest Enets);
<br>Yeniseian (with Ket);
<br>Chukotko-Kamchatkan (with Chukchi).
<br>Singulatives in this area are less variable than what we observe in Africa, mostly falling in the derivational domain. They are colexified with terms meaning 'eye' in (at least) two language families. At this stage, it is unclear if there are singulatives in other families represented in Siberia (which is to say Tungusic, Eskimo-Aleut, Turkic, Nivkh, Yukaghiric) (Anderson 2006: 267). In any case, it is plausible that singulatives spread by contact across language families, through the long history of nomadism and small-scale multilingualism of Indigenous peoples of Siberia and Northern Europe (Khanina 2021).<br>Another interesting point emerging from the database is that singulatives appear to be a feature of Indo-European beyond Celtic: there are examples from Romance, Germanic, Slavic and Indo-Iranian.<br>(comment: 1 example per IE subgroup)<br>
extract examples from DB: find 1 example per fam (repeat italian example)<br>Further research is needed to assess whether any of these findings involve singulative morphemes, rather than just isolated, unproductive singulative word forms. The present work contributes to clarifying the status of Germanic.<br>Finally, the database also reports singulatives in languages that are genetically and geographically disparate. These include:<br>
<br>Algic languages in North America (Fox);
<br>Arawakan and Chibchan, two families in the Amazonian region of South America (Tariana,...);
<br>Niger-Congo, especially the Bantu phylum, which covers much of the centre and south of Africa.
<br>Sino-Tibetan in East Asia (Cantonese);
<br>Austronesian in "Papunesia", which is to say South East Asia and Oceania (Nehan and others).
<br>There is less known about the presence of singulatives in these areas. More research is needed to determine whether they are genuinely rare, or rather underreported.<br>At present, the database reports no singulatives in Australia, West Africa, Meso-America, or among signed languages.<br>(comment: make a map)<br>
Make a map with markers for named languages + 2 areal clusters<br><br>Turning to the morphological expression of singulative,:it varies across languages, with a strong tendency towards suffixes.<br>Suffixes account for 91% of the examples in the database (Nurmio 2023: 11). Other possible markers of singulatives are: prefixes, circumfixes, and stem alternations.<br><br>(Examples adapted from Nurmio 2023: 12-15)<br><br>I now address markers that carry diminutive and singulative meaning, touching on: types of markers, representative languages, and varying degrees of grammaticalization.<br>The distribution of marker type mirrors that of singulatives overall, with the same strong preponderance for suffixes.<br>In terms of geographic distribution, the overlap is mostly seen in languages from the two tentative areal clusters: "Chad-Ethiopia" (North/East Africa, Middle East); and Siberia/Lapland. We also observe the overlap in a handful of "isolated" languages (isolated in so far as the data collection says nothing about wider distribution yet): Ojibwe (Algic), Baule (Bantu), Kuna (Chibchan).<br><br>
<br>Tigre (first cluster):
<br>Northern Mansi (second cluster):
<br>Ojibwe:
<br>Baule:
<br>Kuna:
<br>The overlap of singulative/diminutive includes diminutives with occasional, more or less lexicalized uses as singulatives; grammaticalized singulatives whose distinctiveness flies under the radar; and markers that fall somewhere in between these two extremes. In other words, it includes true diminutives with some singulative uses, and true singulatives. Thus, closer analysis of the data would dissolve some of this overlap at a synchronic level. In its stead, the relation between the singulative and diminutive would be absent, or historical, depending on the case. (See also <a data-href="1.1.6 Diminutive and singulative overlap" href="draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.6-diminutive-and-singulative-overlap.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">1.1.6 Diminutive and singulative overlap</a>)<br><br>This section turns to overlapping gender/singulative, addressing: types of marker, genders associated with units, and representative languages.<br>The distribution of marker types is similar to that of singulatives overall, albeit with markedly less skewing towards suffixes. More precisely, prefixes and circumfixes become proportionally more common. <br>(comment: add stats)<br>Overlapping expression of gender and singulative is mostly observed in Afro-Asiatic (such as Arabic, and the Chadic branch).<br><br><br>(Adapted from Ryding 2005:X, Newman 1990:X.)<br>The unpublished database also illustrates its presence in Indo-European languages outside Celtic, such as in Italian. Our data does show that there are singulative word forms derived with a gendered suffix, Italian -ino. The suffix is derives masculine words, regardless of the gender of the base. Whether this suffix is a true singulative is currently unknown.<br><br><br>(adapted from Dires p.c.; Nurmo et al forth.)<br>Pairing others than feminine/unit are also possible.<br>For example, Fox (Algic) has two grammatical genders, animate and inanimate (Goddard 2002). Fox has some word pair that alternate in gender, such that the inanimate noun expresses a mass or collectivity, and the animate noun expresses a unit.<br><br><br>(Adapted from Goddard 2002: 213)<br>Another example is reported by Acquaviva 2016: 1173 -- reassignment in noun class 5 creates singulative forms in Swahili (Niger-Congo, Bantu).  (Noun classes and their relation to the study of grammatical gender are discussed in XXX.)<br>See section XXX for a more in-depth discussion of the gender/singulative overlap.<br><br>Singulative's emerge through reanalysis of ... (and +- grammaticalization)<br>
<br>DIM marker
<br>lexical item (in compound noun), eg 'eye' in Siberian area
<br>gender markers (or feature bundle, as in Arabic)
<br>reverse markers. (Maybe PL -&gt; reverse -&gt; SGV?)
<br>(anything else?)
<br><br>In conclusion, recent research moves away from viewing singulatives as rare, and suggests that they are more common than previously thought, but still critically under-reported.<br>This thesis elucidates the status of singulatives in all West Germanic languages amenable to research, especially as it pertains to the diminutive/singulative and gender/singulative overlaps.<br><br><br>
<br>
<br>Nilotic is a proposed sub-branch of Nilo-Saharan. There is more support for the coherence of Nilotic as a genetic grouping (Güldemann 2018: 285-287), than for Nilo-Saharan (Güldemann 2018: 81).<a href="about:blank#fnref-1-b91ba2b1ff6401ee" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.1.8-typology.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.1.8 Typology.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:30:25 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.2 Defining and sampling West Germanic]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>In this section, I define West Germanic, and discuss two controversial aspects of its composition: where to draw boundaries between languages (specifically the boundaries of German and Scots), and whether to include English- and Dutch- based creoles. I wrap up the section by explaining the motivations for my language sample.<br>West Germanic is a branch of Indo-European (Glottolog: West Germanic). Living West Germanic languages are: Afrikaans, English, Frisian, Dutch, "German" (which can be further broken up in High and Low German), Scots, Yiddish, several English-based creoles such as Jamaican Patois, and some Dutch-based creoles such as Javindo.<br>According to Stifles 2018: 15-17, English, Frisian, Dutch, Low German and High German can be grouped under West Germanic, because they share innovations that support the existence of a proto-West Germanic stage. Afrikaans is included insofar as it is a descendant of Dutch (Heeringa et al 2015: 4), as Scots is to Old English (Bills 2009: 27-30), and Yiddish to High German (Beider 2018: 276). There is a high degree of consensus regarding the fact that Afrikaans, English, Frisian, Dutch, German and Yiddish are West Germanic. However, disagreements remain regarding their exact sorting into sub-families. For example, Bills (2009: 29) summarizes the competing theories regarding the ancestor of Old English: Anglo-Frisian, or Ingvaeonic.<br>Putting together a list of West Germanic languages runs into the classic problem of dividing languages and dialects, which especially affects German and Scots. (It is also pertinent to English, considering the existence of World Englishes and the contentious divide between them and English-based Creoles. I leave out discussing in detail, however, since it will become apparent that English is excluded from my sample anyway.)<br>My prerogative for treating German as a single language is that speakers of High and Low German both orient towards similar standards based on High German (Pickl 2023), and there are no movements of language secessionism (striving to establish a variety as a language, rather than as a dialect (Pradilla 1999)). Speakers of both view themselves and each other as speakers of "German". This also holds for speakers of Swiss German (Watts 1999).<br>&nbsp;Meanwhile, Scots is a language in its own right, and not a dialect of English, insofar as it speakers mostly consider it a distinct language (Bills 2009: 13). It has several distinctive features that iconize a boundary between Scots and English (DSL: A Language or a Dialect?). Here the key is not just the volume of differences, but what they represent socially. Additionally, the divide between varieties of English and of Scots is several centuries old; modern Scots descends from Older Scots (Bills 209: 22), and the fact its speakers treat it as a language is far from a recent phenomenon. All in all, Scots is subject to language secessionism, and the perception of its speakers holds more weight than the perception of non-speakers, when it comes to defining it as a language or dialect. Ergo, I treat it as a language.<br>&nbsp;&nbsp;The arguments that support my sorting of German and Scots are of a social nature, because "languages" are ideological constructs whose boundaries are created through shared norms (i.e. standards), and shared identification as speakers of a given language (Irvine &amp; Gal 2000). The amount of internal variation in a so-called language, and differentiation from neighboring languages, may range from minor, or so great as to impede mutual intelligibility. Internal variation is not immaterial to the status of a variety, but shaped by it, and vice versa, in a feedback loop. More concretely, language standardization results in shared orientation towards a norm, which in turns results in dialect levelling, and dialect levelling further strenghtens the idea that there is "(only) one language".<br>Ultimately, the status of a variety as language or dialect is primarily a sociopolitical matter. I take the position that linguists cannot abstract away from the real-world status of varieties, and authoritatively declare varieties to be dialects or language, on the basis of mutual intelligibility, or degree of lexical/grammatical similarity.<br>In short, I treat German and Scots as languages, because their speakers treat them as languages. (In closing, whether to treat German as a single language, is a separate matter from whether variation within German would be worth studying. This is addressed further in this section.)<br>A second point of contention regarding the composition of the West Germanic family, is whether English- and Dutch-based creoles belong to it. Excluding English- and Dutch-based creoles from West Germanic rests on viewing the emergence of creoles as a result of broken transmission, radical grammatical simplification, and other processes specific to creoles; in short, it based on creole exceptionalism (DeGraff 2003). However, my point of view aligns with uniformitarians, who view creoles as emerging through the same processes as non-creoles (DeGraff 2003). There is no more reason to exclude Jamaican Patois from West Germanic because of the effect of intense linguistic contact &amp; mixture involved in its history, as there are reasons to exclude English for the very same reason.<br>The language sample for my study comprises: Afrikaans, Frisian, Dutch, German, Scots and Yiddish. "German" is effectively mostly Standard, High German. "Frisian" is West Frisian, simply because the available Frisian corpora represent this variety.<br>I exclude English, English- and Dutch-based creoles, as well as Low German. I will motivate the exclusions, before moving on to justifying the inclusions.<br>(comment: exhaustivity)<br>
does that cover all my exclusions? check what are all WG varieties per Glottolog and other sources <br>The exclusion of English is a result of the absence of reports of singulative forms in the literature. As a speaker of English, I judge that there are no equivalents to the singulative forms seen in other West Germanic languages.<br>Similarly, I have not found reports of singulative forms in English- or Dutch-based creoles, and corpus availability for these languages is severely limited. Dutch-based creoles have a higher likelihood of having singulative forms than English-based ones, since there is evidence that Dutch has singulative forms. However, Dutch-based creoles are dormant, or near dormancy, which makes finding speakers near impossible (Glottolog: Berbice Creole Dutch, Javindo, Negerhollands, Petjo, Skepi Creole Dutch, Zeeuws). My research project requires access to pre-existing corpora, and speakers to consult; I lack access to both of these, for all relevant creoles. The motivations to research singulative forms in English- and Dutch-based creoles, are not high enough to overcome the challenge that data collection would represent for a project of my scale.<br>The exclusion of Low German, and dialectal variation of the sampled varieties, stems from the need to limit the thematic scope and timeframe of my work. Additionally, available corpora do not have sufficient breadth and/or metadata to support dialectal research across all languages. The corpora I found permit the collection of multiple varieties of Dutch, German, Scots and Yiddish, and whether multiple varieties of Afrikaans and (West) Frisian are represented in their respective corpora is unclear. However, only one corpus allows targetting specific dialects. Thus, even if the corpora include data from multiple varieties, their metadata and/or search engine does not support dialectological research, as is. Dialectological research on singulatives in West Germanic could leverage pre-existing corpora to some extent, but it would require creating a new corpus.<br>Since there are significant lexical and grammatical differences between Low and High German, and diminutives are subject to dialectal variation (at least in Dutch, German and Yiddish; see next section), it is entirely possible that dialectal research would uncover greater diversity in singulative forms than what my project establishes. Although I do not have the means to conduct research on dialectal variation, I hope that this work can serve as a baseline for such research in the future.<br>Moving on to included languages: I have selected Afrikaans, Dutch, Frisian, German, Scots and Yiddish. The data available mostly represent standard varieties, but regional/non-standard data is mixed in (and cannot easily be excluded). Frisian is really West Frisian (since the available corpora represent this variety), and German is effectively High German. Scots and Yiddish's spelling is far less standardized than the other varieties, so Scots and Yiddish corpora showcase regional variation. The data from my corpora thus has to include some dialect data, even if the approach is micro-typological rather than dialectological.<br>I have selected Afrikaans, Dutch, Frisian, German, Scots and Yiddish, because I have access to suitable corpora for all of them, and this sample brings me close to an exhaustive coverage of West Germanic. Setting aside Scots for a moment, there are reports of singulative forms for all these languages, and modest differences between them according to literature. I anticipate that I will uncover more differences as I compare data from each language. Hence, no language seems redundant to research, or likely to become a dead end.<br>However, returning to Scots, whether there are singulative forms is entirely uncertain. I include it nonetheless because it is an under-researched language with allegedly prolific use of diminutives (Millar 2018: 142-143); perhaps there are no reports of singulatives because there are none to report, perhaps there are too few publications on Scots grammar for them to see the light of day. More generally, I include marginalized languages (i.e. Scots, Frisian and Yiddish) and overlook the shortcomings of their corpora, because contributing to their description is a goal of my research.<br>Overall, my sample effectively provides an overview of West Germanic, includes diverse manifestations of singulatives, and puts marginalized languages on the same footing as languages that have a stronger social status. The sample is designed to make contributions to typology, and a modest contribution to the description of West Germanic languages, including some under-researched varieties.<br>(comment: contribution to typology)<br>
Elaborate here and/or earlier in the section re: contribution to typology]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.2-defining-and-sampling-west-germanic.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.2 Defining and sampling West Germanic.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:30:06 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3 Singulatives in West Germanic]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>This section presents literature relevant to singulatives in West Germanic. It addresses whether there are any claims that singulatives exist in each language, and which marking strategies have (or might have) this function. I rely on grammars and academic articles. The academic articles I rely on generally concern number or derivation. Overall, the literature I consulted suggests that singulatives are expressed through diminutive suffixes, and variance in grammatical gender. There is no evidence of other strategies; I show that there are no singulatives in the inflectional domain, for example.<br>For all languages, I discuss whether diminutive morphemes might behave as singulatives. There are reports that they do in Dutch, Frisian, German and Yiddish, and hence they also might in closely related languages. This is nothing typologically unusual, as diminutives and singulatives overlap in several languages (Nurmio 2023: 6). The table (X) outlines all the diminutive morphemes included, and excluded from my research, with all allomorphs and prototypical examples.<br><br><br>
Table (X)<br>(comment re: kindele)<br>
Todo confirm accuracy of gloss<br>I also address gender as a potential form of "singulative". There are words in Frisian that can refer to units when in common gender, and to masses when in neuter gender. Accordingly, I look for similar phenomena in other languages that have grammatical gender. This pattern is a less typical way unit/mass contrasts can be expressed through grammatical gender (whereas the most cross-linguistically common pattern seems to be that the feminine expresses units, as in Afro-Asiatic languages (Nurmio 2023: 14)).<br>Thus, the singulative strategies that I look for in my sample are: use of diminutives (X), and gender alternations (X).<br><br><br>(Adapted from ([Broekhuis &amp; Keizer 2012: 33](<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf > page=55" data-href="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf#page=55" href="draft/7.-references/literature/broekhuis-keizer-2012-vol-1.pdf#page=55" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1, p.33</a>)))<br><br> (Frisian TP Gender)<br>Additionally, I investigated whether there might be singulatives in the inflectional domain according to current literature. I found no cases of marked singular forms derived from plurals in any targeted language. Rather, on nouns, plurals are marked through suffixes, and singular remains unmarked, as in (13) and (14).<br>Less commonly, nouns are unmarked for number, as in (15), or their plural marking is expressed through stem changes, as in (16). Similarly to nouns, agreement between nouns and dependent parts of speech (such as adjectives, articles) do not exhibit patterns where singular is marked, and plural unmarked: for instance, in German, singular and plural agreement are equally marked, and fused with gender. Gender categories get conflated in the plural.<br>(For Afrikaans, see Donaldson 1993: 69-84; for Dutch, Booij 2019: 17; for Frisian, Taalportaal: Number, Tiersma 1999: 49-52; for German, Dodd 2003: 50-53; for Scots, Millar 2018: 141-142; and for Yiddish, Birnbaum 1979: 228-231.)<br>
<br><br><br>(Adapted from Donaldson 2008: 44, 78; Dodd 2003: 51-52)<br>Agreement where singular and plural are equally marked:<br>(9)&nbsp;&nbsp; &nbsp;German: ...<br>
<br>Hence I exclude number inflection as a source of singulatives, and I do not address it in the sections below.<br>Each section concludes with an overview of the marking strategies that are worth investigating, based on information assembled from available publications.<br><br>
<br>
<br>Some of these forms are allomorphs of the same morpheme, but it is unclear which ones.<a href="about:blank#fnref-1-b91ba2b1ff6401ee" class="footnote-backref footnote-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">↩︎</a>
]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3-singulatives-in-west-germanic.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3 Singulatives in West Germanic.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:32:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3.1 Afrikaans]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Whether Afrikaans has singulative is not established in current literature. There is no mention of such in grammars of Afrikaans (Donaldson 1993, Taalportaal: Preliminaries).<br>Afrikaans has the diminutive morpheme -tjie. It is possible that this morpheme also has the function of singulative, since morphemes with overlapping diminutive/singulative are found in other West Germanic varieties (see Dutch, Frisian, German and Frisian). Initial data found in Donaldson 1993: 87-95 is promising.<br>
Donaldson 1993: 94 includes diminutive forms that select mass nouns and many of them fall under similar semantic areas as Dutch diminutive/singulatives: (portions of) beverages and foods. It is unclear if these examples can have unit readings, an affective connotation, or both simultaneously. This is something to elucidate with a language expert.<br><br><br>(Adapted from Donaldson 1993: 94. Base words added for comparison.)<br>Furthermore, this quote from Donaldson 1993: 91 adds support to the idea that -tjie might act as singulative:<br>
(footnote 41) Drank is 'drink' as a collective whereas an individual 'drink' is a drankie."
<br>Additionally, De Belder presents one example of an Afrikaans word with the morpheme -tjie, and a unit reading:<br><br><br>(Adapted from De Belder 2011: 184. Base word added for comparison.)<br>Use of gender to mark the singulative, parallel to what is seen in Frisian, is not possible in Afrikaans, given that it lacks grammatical gender altogether (Donaldson 1993: 56). It can be excluded without further research.<br>comment: contact<br>
Address contact with Bantu, effect on diminutives? Eg look at Di Garbo's dissertation<br>On the other hand, Afrikaans has long been in contact with multiple Bantu languages (such as isiNdebele), and Khoe languages (such as Khoekhoe) of South Africa (Mahlangu 2016, Christie 2002).<br>Languages from both of these families feature systems of grammatical gender. Gender systems may be sex-based (with distinction between masculine and feminine at minimum) or non-sex-based (with semantic distinction that are far more numerous and varied than sex-based systems). Non-sex based gender systems are often called systems of noun classes, and whether they are instances of "gender" is a source of terminological and conceptual debate. I will not delve into this, and simply follow Di Garbo 2014: 61-80 in talking of (Bantu) noun classes as a subtype of gender.<br>Bantu noun classes&nbsp;involve a high number of classes (often more than 10), which are expressed through prefixes and fused with number (Kihm 2002), whereas Khoe languages feature triads of feminine, masculine and neuter grammatical genders (Witzlack-Makarevich 2019: 14). It is possible that there are contact-induced effects of grammatical gender, on Afrikaans singulatives. This would involve singulatives expressed through gender or noun class in the source language, resulting in parallel constructions in Afrikaans (direct loans, or calques). It is also worth noting that we can observe singulative use of Bantu noun classes that express the diminutive (i.e. in Baoule, Nurmio et al forth.). However, studying this would require acquaintance with Bantu and Khoe languages, and perhaps the creation of a new corpus, both of which exceed the means at my disposal. Future study on this topic could rely on Di Garbo's work on gender and evaluative morphology (hence diminutives) in languages of Africa.<br>(comment: noun classes VS gender)<br>
Re first sentence, "Bantu noun classes&nbsp;involve a high number of classes (often more than 10), which are expressed through prefixes and fused with number (Kihm 2002), whereas Khoe languages feature triads of feminine, masculine and neuter grammatical genders (Witzlack-Makarevich 2019: 14)."<br>
SN: this is controversial in Bantu, many pp (including us in our project) speak of noun classes rather than gender. Di Garbo is likely to have a discussion of this? SN: + other refs possibly, check our Bantu presentation <br>Thus, according to available publications, it is worth investigating whether -tjie, -ie might have singular usages, and singulative expression through gender change can be immediately excluded.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3.1-afrikaans.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3.1 Afrikaans.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:34:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3.2 Dutch]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The diminutive morpheme -je can derive singulative forms, based on information from the following publications: Broekhuis &amp; Keizer 2012, Donaldson 2008, Taalportaal, De Belder 2008 &amp; 2011, Ott 2011, Jurafsky 1996. These sources discuss the morpheme's phonology, productivity and/or meaning range. Most address the singulative function of the morpheme, although they refer to the process as "itemizing", "individuation" or "individualization". Words derived with -je are always of neuter gender (TP Dutch DIM).<br>Broekhuis &amp; Keizer (2012: 32-33) state that -je can be used to derive count nouns, although with constrained productivity because some resulting words "sound marked" (see (6)). What the authors mean by "marked" is left vague; the examples might be unacceptable, odd or accepted with hesitation. I will need to test the words myself to clarify this.<br><br><br>(Adapted from Broekhuis &amp; Keizer 2012: 32-33. Note that it is unclear if the asterisk has its conventional meaning of grammatical unacceptability.)<br>Similarly, Taalportaal's page Nominal suffixation: diminutives states that -je is "is used to itemize certain mass nouns (particularly varieties of food and drink) which take on the meaning of one item of that substance when they bear the diminutive ending". Donaldson 2008: 62-63 reports the same information. De Belder (2008: 119-120; 2011: 88-89, 92) states that mass words with diminutives do not have mass readings, and do have unit readings.<br>Dutch has another diminutive marker, -el, which may have singulative uses. It is a relic that occurs in Southern Dutch, as in:<br><br><br>(Adapted from TP Dutch DIM)<br>I have not come across any reports of singulative readings for words derived with -el, and I do not investigate it because it is regional.<br>Dutch has two grammatical genders, common and neuter (Booij 2019: 32). Singulative marking through gender is thus possible. The gender of nouns in Dutch is only apparent through agreement with other word classes, such as articles. Sections on gender in Dutch grammars do not address gender expressing individuation (e.g. Booij 2019: 32-34). Nonetheless, Taalportaal states that semantic pairs where unit readings are in common gender, and mass readings are in neuter gender, are found in Dutch, as in the following example.<br><br><br>(Adapted from TP Dutch Gender)<br>Note that this is in contrast with the fact that words derived with diminutive endings are always neuter (Booij 2016: 34), including those with singulative function. To what extent Dutch marks singulative through gender will be one of my research questions.<br>In summary, current literature firmly establishes that -je is a diminutive morpheme with singulative usages, but there is no systematic description of it. To what extent gender plays a role in unit/mass contrasts is an open question worth investigating. Words where unit reading is in common gender, and mass reading is in neuter gender, are expected.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3.2-dutch.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3.2 Dutch.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 10:39:59 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3.3 English]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>I have not found any sources discussing whether English has singulatives. In what follows, I explain my reasoning for concluding that English has no singulatives.<br>First, unit/mass contrasts through gender are out of the question, since English has no grammatical gender. It only has gender distinctions in pronouns (van Gelderen, 2010: 24).<br>Additionally, works that explore the semantic and pragmatic range expressed by English diminutives do not speak of individuation (Kardoš Stojanović YEAR?, Schneider 2012, Sifianou 1992).<br>Finally, consider English diminutives that are equivalents to singulative forms in other West Germanic languages, and compare them.<br>
In my judgement, the equivalents are barely acceptable (e.g.: ? snow-ie, ? grass-ie, ? wood-let, ? sand-let,...). When they are acceptable, interpretations that have to do with smallness, endearment and pejoration are available, and if the reading refers to a unit, it must be a small unit. The 'unit' reading is available partly due to the fact that diminutives turn mass nouns into count nouns (compare *have drink-ie, and have a drink-ie).<br>
The meaning 'unit' cannot be separated from the other semantic layers of the diminutive (either denotation of 'small' and/or, especially for -ie, colloquial connotation), whereas singulative forms in other West Germanic can refer to units regardless of size (according to glosses in the literature; in all fairness, to what extent this is true is an open question my project will elucidate).<br>(comment: drink-ie)<br>
SN: with 'a drink-ie', it's a very marked form (humour, colloquial, etc.), not sure if smallness is very central?]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3.3-english.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3.3 English.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:34:39 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3.4 Frisian]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Singulatives are not discussed in Tiersma 1999, a reference grammar of Frisian. However, singulatives are discussed on three pages of Taalportaal (-DIM, Gender and Number). Taalportaal is online scientific grammar of Afrikaans, Dutch and Frisian. Their page -DIM states that the diminutive morpheme -tje can take mass nouns and turn them into count nouns. The derived words are individuated, as in the example gers 'grass', gerske 'grass stalk'. Words that bear -tje are always neuter (TP Frisian -DIM).<br>Singulatives uses of words with -tje are also discussed in Hoekstra 1984: 134-135, 1998: 84. Several examples formed with -tje, that refer to unit nouns and are derived from non-count nouns are given.<br><br>
(X)<br>
<br>ark-je 'tool'
<br>praatsje 'chat'
<br>túch-je 'speck of dust'
<br>gers-ke 'blade of grass'
<br>sûkelaadsje 'piece of chocolate'
<br>grús-ke 'candy'
<br>kryt-sje 'piece of chalk'
<br>hout-sje '??? TBD'
<br>swilk-je 'table oil-cloth'
<br>reau-ke 'cup and saucer'<br>
(Hoekstra 1998: 84)
<br><br>
(X)<br>
<br>bierke 'beer'
<br>gerske 'blade of grass
<br>grúske 'candy'
<br>gomke 'piece of gum'
<br>krytsje 'piece of chalk'
<br>siedsje 'seed'
<br>praatsje 'chat'
<br>sûkelaadsje 'piece of chocolate'
<br>arkje 'tool'
<br>jonke '??? TBD'
<br>túchje 'speck of dust'
<br>konjakje 'glass of cognac'<br>
(Hoekstra 1984: 134)
<br>(comment: merge lists)<br>
todo merge both lists to cut out repetitions<br>Frisian has two grammatical genders, common and neuter; the gender of a noun is apparent through its agreement pattern (TP Frisian Gender). Taalportaal's page Gender states that words referring to units can be derived through gender change to common, as in the following:<br><br><br>(Adapted from TP Frisian Gender)<br>It is surprising that unit nouns are common and mass nouns neuter, whereas unit nouns formed with the diminutive ending -tje are actually neuter (Hoekstra 2016: 2456). This makes it unlikely that unit/mass pairs differentiated through gender are the result of erosion of -tje. The fact that common gender singulatives are found in Frisian is what motivates me to look for gender-marked singulatives in other West Germanic varieties, and to stretch my use of the term "singulative" to include such patterns, even though they do not involve the addition of a marker. This is a pain point in my current work and will require revision of my terminology, and better justification, backed by typological data.<br>In summary, current literature establishes that the singulative is expressed through -ke and allomorphs, and through common gender. There is room to uncover more information about the working of both of these marking strategies.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3.4-frisian.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3.4 Frisian.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:35:14 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3.5 German]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>The literature I consulted mostly does not address singulatives uses of German diminutives, whether it is in grammars (Durrell 2002: 497; Donaldson 2006: 41-42; Dodd 2003: X), or in works on derivation (Barz 2016: 2396) or on the evolution of diminutives (Lameli 2018, Nieuwenhuis 1985). However, forms derived with -chen have singulative uses according to Ott 2011. The base word has a mass reading, whereas the -chen form has a unit reading:<br><br><br>(Adapted from Ott 2011: 6)<br>The examples given fall under the categories of foods, liquids and materials. "Most mass nouns" can derive a unit noun with -chen (Ott 2011: 23). This suggests that singulative uses of -chen might be productive, and that it will be possible to find significantly more examples than what Ott 2011 presents. It is worth nothing that words bearing -chen are always neuter (Dodd 2003: 137).<br>On the other hand, there are no reports of other diminutive morphemes (such as -lein, -erl and other forms given in Donaldson 2006: 41) being used for individuation. I exclude them from the scope of my research because they are dialectal, and less likely to occur in my corpora. Whether they allow unit readings like -chen is ripe for future research.<br>German has a system of grammatical gender, consisting of masculine, feminine and neuter (Dodd 2003: 25). Thus, it could use gender to express the singulative. There is no mention of this happening in sources on German grammar (source). If it does happen, the parallel to Frisian would be to use masculine or feminine to refer to units, and the neuter to refer to a mass, but the gender-reading pairs could work out differently. It is worth investigating.<br>Overall, there is ground to investigate possible singulative uses of the diminutive morpheme -chen, and of gender alternation.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3.5-german.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3.5 German.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 10:46:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3.6 Scots]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>I have not found any indication that singulatives exist in Scots. However, there are few publications on Scots grammar available. Given Scots' status as rather under-researched, one cannot be sure that singulative strategies are non-existent.<br>Millar 2018 is a grammar on Scots. It states that words with diminutive endings occur more frequently in Scots than in English (Millar 2018: 142-143); this increased frequency makes it possible that diminutives have a greater range of semantic functions than English, which could include individuation. Yet there is no data illustrating individuation in this source, nor is there mention of it. Diminutive morphemes that express the singulatives are established in several of Scots' sister varieties, so looking for parallel constructions might uncover the presence of singulatives.<br>A frequently used diminutive is more likely to have a wide spectrum of semantic and pragmatic usages, and by extension include singulative usages, than infrequent diminutives. Hence, a sensible priority is to investigate the most frequent diminutives, and if constraints oblige, forego investigating less frequent diminutives. -ie is the most frequent diminutive per Millar 2018: 143. Millar also lists -ock as a diminutive (with the variant -ag used in Caithness), and does not list any other diminutives. I extrapolate that -ock ranks among the most common Scots diminutives, and the other diminutive I am aware of, -le (whose variants are: -l/-il/-ill/-al/-ol/-ul-/yl), is left unmentioned by Millar 2018, because it is markedly less frequent.<br>Thus, I investigate -ie and -ock, because they are frequent, and more likely to be used as singulatives. On the other hand, I exclude -le (and all of its variants), because its lower frequency makes it less likely to have singulative uses. It is also worth mentioning that some of the variants of -le, and -le itself, would be extremely time-consuming to research, due to the high volume of words ending in -le that are not diminutives in the corpus. (Consider words such as: giggle, possible, tale,...). Furthermore, I exclude variants of -ock, because they are either historical (-oc), or regional (-och, -ec, -eck, -ac, -ack, -ic, -ick are used in Shetland, and -k, -ag, -og in Caithness) (DSL -ock). This places them outside of the scope of my work.<br>There is no system of grammatical gender in Scots. This much is clear based on Millar 2018: 144, which states that there are only gender distinctions on pronouns, much like in English. Accordingly, singulative categorically cannot be expressed through gender.<br>In principle, Scottish Gaelic could be a source of singulatives in Scots due to contact between the varieties. However, Scottish Gaelic belongs to the Goidelic branch of the Celtic family, and singulative suffixes only became productive in the Brittonic branch, in varieties such as Breton, Cornish and Welsh (Nurmio 2016: 9). There are very few singulative-plural pairs in Scottish Gaelic, and they are not productive:<br><br><br>(Acquaviva 2006: 34-35)<br>Number in Scottish Gaelic is, instead, overwhelmingly marked through palatalization and suffixes expressing the plural (Lamb 2001: 26). Looking for words in Scots that are cognates to Gaelic singulatives is worthwhile, but the likelihood that Scots singulatives will be uncovered this way is low.<br>In summary, it is worthwhile to investigate whether diminutive endings have singular usages in Scots, and whether there are any singulative forms that are the results of contact with Scottish Gaelic. Given the state of research, there is no guaranty that either will uncover singulative forms. On the other hand, there is no use researching singulative strategies involving gender.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3.6-scots.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3.6 Scots.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 10:49:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1.3.7 Yiddish]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Grammars of Yiddish do not describe the singulative directly, even in their sections on diminutives (Katz 1987, Birnbaum 2016). -l and -ele (regional variants -aly, -ely) are both diminutive morphemes. -ele can express a greater degree of diminution than -l (as will be seen in example (14)), and also gets called 'minutive' (Birnbaum 2016: 238-240). The morphemes -l and -ele do have singulative uses, as shown in examples from Neuberg 2016, Jurafsky 1996, and Birnbaum 2016: 238-240. Note that words with -l or -ele are always neuter (all diminutive forms given in Birnbaum 1979: 238-240 are given with a neuter article, dus).<br>For -l, Jurafsky 1996: 536 provides an example taken from Birnbaum 1979:<br><br><br>(Adapted from <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jurafsky 1996.pdf > page=5" data-href="Jurafsky 1996.pdf#page=5" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jurafsky-1996.pdf#page=5" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Jurafsky 1996: 536</a>)<br>For -ele, Neuberg (2016: 2472) provides a few singulatives examples:<br><br><br>(Adapted from Neuberg 2016: 2472)<br>A few examples can also be found in Birnbaum 2016: 240 (adapted):<br><br><br>(Adapted from Birnbaum 2016: 240)<br>-ele's form vary from one Yiddish dialect to another (known variants: -aly, -ely), and it is likely that the range of forms with this morpheme, that have singuative uses, varies by dialect too. As stated before, however, I do not have the means to conduct dialectal research. Additionally, Yiddish has diminutive morphemes beyond -l and -ele: these are -(e)nyu, -(e)shi, and -ke (Neuberg 2016: 2472). There are no reports of these having singulative uses, and Neuberg's excerpt makes me believe they are less frequent than -ele and -l, and hence more likely to have a limited semantic range that does not include singulative uses. They seem mostly hypocoristic. I prioritize the morphemes which have known singulative uses, and leave the investigation of -(e)nyu, -e(shi) and -ke to future research.<br>Yiddish generally has three genders: masculine, feminine and neuter (Birnbaum 2016: 227), Some dialects have reduced this system to two (losing neuter &amp; retaining masculine and feminine (Kahn 2015: 669)), or even lost gender entirely (Belk, Kahn &amp; Szendroi 2020).<br>
I did not find any information regarding gender expressing individuation (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Birnbaum 1979.pdf > page=243" data-href="Birnbaum 1979.pdf#page=243" href="draft/7.-references/literature/birnbaum-1979.pdf#page=243" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Birnbaum 1979: 227-228</a>, Neuberg 2016, Katz 1987: 47-53). However, it remains possible and worth investigating, especially if I can find a parallel in German.<br>In summary, the morphemes -l and -ele are the best leads, as multiple sources showcase their singulative use. Singulative use of grammatical gender is in principle possible and deserves inspection, although it may prove to be absent.]]></description><link>draft/1.-background-literature/1.3.7-yiddish.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/1. Background literature/1.3.7 Yiddish.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 11:35:18 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[2. Research plan]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>(introduction metatext)]]></description><link>draft/2.-research-plan/2.-research-plan.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/2. Research plan/2. Research plan.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 10:55:57 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[2.1 Research questions]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>to rewrite]]></description><link>draft/2.-research-plan/2.1-research-questions.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/2. Research plan/2.1 Research questions.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Wed, 15 Jan 2025 08:26:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[2.2 Materials]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>to rewrite and update]]></description><link>draft/2.-research-plan/2.2-materials.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/2. Research plan/2.2 Materials.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 10:56:09 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[2.3 Methods]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>to rewrite]]></description><link>draft/2.-research-plan/2.3-methods.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/2. Research plan/2.3 Methods.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 10:56:13 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[7. References]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>
<br>*pdf not migrated

<br>(how to access if no PDF)


<br>if sth is missing here, check <a data-href="7.X Edited volumes" href="draft/7.-references/7.x-edited-volumes.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">7.X Edited volumes</a><br><br><br>Acquaviva, Paolo. 2006. Goidelic inherent plurals and the morphosemantics of number. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Acquaviva 2006.pdf" data-href="Acquaviva 2006.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/acquaviva-2006.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Acquaviva, Paolo. 2016. Singulatives. HSK Word-Formation. An International Handbook of the Languages of Europe, ed. Peter O. Müller, Ingeborg Ohnheiser, Susan Olsen &amp; Franz Rainer, 1171–1183. Berlin: Mouton de Gruyter. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Acquaviva 2016.pdf" data-href="Acquaviva 2016.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/acquaviva-2016.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://corpora.uni-leipzig.de/en?corpusId=afr_mixed_2014" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://corpora.uni-leipzig.de/en?corpusId=afr_mixed_2014" target="_blank">Afrikaans Mixed Corpus</a><br>Allan 1980. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Allan 1980.pdf" data-href="Allan 1980.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/allan-1980.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Anderson 2006, chapter in Linguistic Areas - Convergence in Historical and Typological Perspective<br><br>Badawi et al 2015, Modern Written Arabic (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Badawi et al 2015.pdf > page=1" data-href="Badawi et al 2015.pdf#page=1" href="draft/7.-references/literature/badawi-et-al-2015.pdf#page=1" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Barz, Irmhild. 2016. German. Chapter in Word-formation in the individual European languages. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Barz 2016.pdf" data-href="Barz 2016.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/barz-2016.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Beider, Alexander. 2018. Yiddish in Eastern Europe. Chapter in Languages in Jewish Communities, Past and Present.<br>Belk, Zoë, Lily Kahn &amp; Kriszta Eszter Szendrői. 2020. Complete loss of case and gender within two generations: evidence from Stamford Hill Hasidic Yiddish. Article in The Journal of Comparative Germanic Linguistics, volume 23, pp. 271-326.<br>Birnbaum, Solomon A. 1979. Yiddish: a survey and a grammar. 1st edition. University of Toronto Press. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Birnbaum 1979.pdf" data-href="Birnbaum 1979.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/birnbaum-1979.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>
<br>Birnbaum, Solomon A. 2016. Yiddish: a survey and a grammar. 2nd edition. University of Toronto Press.

<br>accessed online thru Helka


<br>Bock, Albert &amp; Benjamin Bruch. 2008. An Outline of the Standard Written Form (SWF) for Cornish. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Bock &amp; Bruch 2008.pdf" data-href="Bock &amp; Bruch 2008.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/bock-&amp;-bruch-2008.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Booij, Geert. 2016. Dutch. Chapter in _Word-formation in the individual European languages. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Booij 2016.pdf" data-href="Booij 2016.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/booij-2016.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Broekhuis, Hans, and Evelien Keizer. 2012. Syntax of Dutch - Nouns and Noun phrases. Volume 1. Amsterdam University Press. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf" data-href="Broekhuis Keizer 2012 vol 1.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/broekhuis-keizer-2012-vol-1.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/dutch-english/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://dictionary.cambridge.org/dictionary/dutch-english/" target="_blank">Cambridge Dutch-English Dictionary</a><br>Christie, Camilla Rose. 2022. Khoekhoe Lexical Borrowings in Regionalised Afrikaans. Article in Stellenbosh Papers in Linguistics Plus, vol. 64, 133-143. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Christie 2022.pdf" data-href="Christie 2022.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/christie-2022.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://coquery.org/index.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://coquery.org/index.html" target="_blank">Coquery</a><br>Corbett, Greville. Number. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Corbett 2001.pdf" data-href="Corbett 2001.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/corbett-2001.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www1.fa.knaw.nl/ksf.html" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www1.fa.knaw.nl/ksf.html" target="_blank">Corpus of Spoken Frisian</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="http://web-corpora.net/YNC/search/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="http://web-corpora.net/YNC/search/" target="_blank">Corpus of Modern Yiddish</a><br>Corpus of Modern Yiddish, Improving the Research Possibilities for Textual Artifacts. <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.uni-regensburg.de/assets/sprache-literatur-kultur/slavistik/sprachwissenschaft/cmy_long_version.pdf" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.uni-regensburg.de/assets/sprache-literatur-kultur/slavistik/sprachwissenschaft/cmy_long_version.pdf" target="_blank">Slides</a>.<br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://dgd.ids-mannheim.de/dgd/pragdb.dgd_extern.welcome?v_session_id=" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://dgd.ids-mannheim.de/dgd/pragdb.dgd_extern.welcome?v_session_id=" target="_blank">Datenbank für Gesprochenes Deutsch</a><br>Dali, Myriam &amp; Éric Mathieu. 2021. Historical Changes in Sub-word Formation: The case of Arabic -a(t). Journal of Historical Syntax, vol. 5, 1-34. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic.pdf" data-href="Dali Mathieu 2021 Arabic.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/dali-mathieu-2021-arabic.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>De Belder, Marijke. 2008, March. Size matters: Towards a syntactic decomposition of countability. In Proceedings of the 27th west coast conference on formal linguistics (pp. 116-122). Cascadilla Proceedings Project; MA: Somerville. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="De Belder 2008.pdf" data-href="De Belder 2008.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/de-belder-2008.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>De Belder, Marijke. 2011. A morphosyntactic decomposition of countability in Germanic. The Journal of Comparative Germanic Linguistics, 14(3), 173-202. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="De Belder 2011 German Dutch.pdf" data-href="De Belder 2011 German Dutch.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/de-belder-2011-german-dutch.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>DeGraff, Michel. 2003. Against Creole Exceptionalism. Language, 79(2): pp.391-410.<br>Dhifallah 2022<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://dsl.ac.uk/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://dsl.ac.uk/" target="_blank">Dictionaries of the Scots Language</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://dsl.ac.uk/about-scots/a-language-or-a-dialect/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://dsl.ac.uk/about-scots/a-language-or-a-dialect/" target="_blank">DSL: A language or a dialect?</a><br>Di Garbo, Francesca. 2014. Gender and its interaction with number and evaluative morphology: An intra- and intergenealogical typological survey of Africa. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Di Garbo 2014.pdf" data-href="Di Garbo 2014.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/di-garbo-2014.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Djalali, Grimm, Clausen, Levin = Grimm et al slides. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm et al slides.pdf" data-href="Grimm et al slides.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-et-al-slides.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>
Djalali, A., Grimm, S., Clausen, D., &amp; Levin, B. (2011). What can be ground? Noun type constructions, and the universal grinder. Proceedings of the Berkeley Linguistics Society. University of California, Berkeley.<br>Dodd, Bill J. 2003. Modern German Grammar. Psychology Press. 454 pages. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Dodd 2003 Grammar.pdf" data-href="Dodd 2003 Grammar.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/dodd-2003-grammar.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Donaldson, Bruce. 1993. A Grammar of Afrikaans. De Gruyter Mouton.<br>Donaldson, Bruce. 2006. German: An Essential Grammar. Routledge.(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Donaldson 2006.pdf" data-href="Donaldson 2006.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/donaldson-2006.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Donaldson, Bruce. 2008. Dutch: A Comprehensive Grammar. Routledge. 2nd edition.<br>Durrell, Martin. 2002. German Grammar and Usage. 4th edition. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Durrell 2002.pdf" data-href="Durrell 2002.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/durrell-2002.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Dutch Web 2020 Corpus, Sketch Engine.<br><br><br><br>Galeas 2004. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Galeas 2004.pdf" data-href="Galeas 2004.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/galeas-2004.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.ids-mannheim.de/en/digspra/corpus-linguistics/projects/corpus-development/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.ids-mannheim.de/en/digspra/corpus-linguistics/projects/corpus-development/" target="_blank">German Reference Corpus</a><br>German Web 2020 Corpus, Sketch Engine.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/berb1259" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/berb1259" target="_blank">Glottolog 4.8 Berbice Creole Dutch</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/javi1237" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/javi1237" target="_blank">Glottolog 4.8&nbsp; Javindo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/nege1244" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/nege1244" target="_blank">Glottolog 4.8&nbsp; Negerhollands</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/petj1238" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/petj1238" target="_blank">Glottolog 4.8&nbsp; Petjo</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/skep1238" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/skep1238" target="_blank">Glottolog 4.8&nbsp; Skepi Creole Dutch</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/west2793" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/west2793" target="_blank">Glottolog 4.8 West Germanic</a><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/zeeu1238" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://glottolog.org/resource/languoid/id/zeeu1238" target="_blank">Glottolog 4.8 Zeeuws</a><br>Goddard 2002, Fox. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Goddard 2002.pdf" data-href="Goddard 2002.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/goddard-2002.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Grimm 2012. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Grimm 2012.pdf" data-href="Grimm 2012.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/grimm-2012.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Güldemann 2010 (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Güldemann 2010.pdf" data-href="Güldemann 2010.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/güldemann-2010.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Güldemann 2018<br><br>Haspelmath, Martin. 2018. How comparative concepts and descriptive linguistic categories are different. Chapter in Aspects of linguistic variation. (= Van Olmen et al)<br>Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017.pdf" data-href="Haspelmath &amp; Karjus 2017.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/haspelmath-&amp;-karjus-2017.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Heeringa, Wilbert, Fede de Wet and Gerhard B. van Huyssteen. Afrikaans and Dutch as Closely Related Languages: A comparison to West Germanic languages and Dutch dialects. Stellenbosch Paper in Linguistics Plus, vol. 47, 1-18.<br>Hoekstra, Jarish. 1984. Ferlytsing en syn njonkenkategoryen. Philologia Frisica anno 1984. Ljouwert: Fryske Akademy, 131-150. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hoekstra 1984.pdf" data-href="Hoekstra 1984.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/hoekstra-1984.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Hoekstra, Jarich. 1998. Fryske wurdfoarming. Fryske Akademy. 183 pages. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hoekstra 1998.pdf" data-href="Hoekstra 1998.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/hoekstra-1998.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Hoekstra, Jarich. 2016. Frisian. Chapter in Volume 4 Word-Formation: An International Handbook of the Languages of Europe, Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter Mouton. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Hoekstra 2016.pdf" data-href="Hoekstra 2016.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/hoekstra-2016.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><br>Irvine, Judith, &amp; Susan T. Gal. 2000. Language ideology and linguistic differentiation. Chapter in Linguistic Anthropology: A Reader, edited by Paul V. Kroskrity. 402-434.<br><br>Jacobs, Neil G. 1995. "Diminutive formation in Yiddish: A syllable-based account." Methodology in Transition, volume 83. (= Irmengaard et al 1995)<br>Jouitteau, Mélanie &amp; Rezac, Milan. 2015. Tester les noms collectifs en Breton, enquête sur le nombre et la numérosité. Article in Mélange en l'honneur de Francis Favereau. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Jouitteau &amp; Rezac 2015.pdf" data-href="Jouitteau &amp; Rezac 2015.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/jouitteau-&amp;-rezac-2015.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Jurafsky, Daniel. 1996. Universal Tendencies in the Semantics of the Diminutive. Language 72(3), 533–578.<br><br>Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf" data-href="Kagan &amp; Nurmio 2024.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kagan-&amp;-nurmio-2024.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Katz, Dovid. 1987. Grammar of the Yiddish Language. Duckworth.&nbsp;<br>Kahn, Lily. 2015. Yiddish. Chapter in Handbook of Jewish Languages<br>Kardoš Stojanović, Aleksandra. Year unknown. "Nominal diminutives in informal Serbian and English." English Studies Today.<br>Khanina 2021 (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Khanina 2021.pdf" data-href="Khanina 2021.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/khanina-2021.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Kihm 2002<br>Kromhout, Jan. 2001. Afrikaans-English, English Afrikaans Dictionary.<br>Kwak, Eun-Joo. 2014 (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Kwak 2014.pdf" data-href="Kwak 2014.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/kwak-2014.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><br>Lamb, William. 2001. Scottish Gaelic. Lincom Europa.<br><br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/02572117.2016.1186892?casa_token=DiYBG5_TXTIAAAAA:0zwKJidYVLljoRTUQd_mCYnLMw0xsVyFpB8tjrGSeBJjfC7AJAoZtFftczuTg8GicTuW-JfkIzk2iFg" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.tandfonline.com/doi/pdf/10.1080/02572117.2016.1186892?casa_token=DiYBG5_TXTIAAAAA:0zwKJidYVLljoRTUQd_mCYnLMw0xsVyFpB8tjrGSeBJjfC7AJAoZtFftczuTg8GicTuW-JfkIzk2iFg" target="_blank">Mahlangu 2016</a><br>Millar, Robert McColl. 2018. Modern Scots: an analytical survey.<br>Mous 2012 Cushitic (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Mous 2012.pdf" data-href="Mous 2012.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/mous-2012.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Muthmann, Gustavv. 1991. Rückläufiges deutsches Wörterbuch: Handbuch der Wortausgänge im Deutschen, mit Beachtung der Wort- und Lautstruktur. De Gruyter.<br><br>Neuberg, Simon. 2016. Yiddish. Chapter in Volume 4 Word-Formation: An International Handbook of the Languages of Europe, Berlin, Boston: De Gruyter Mouton. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Neuberg 2016.pdf" data-href="Neuberg 2016.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/neuberg-2016.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Newman 1990 (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Newman 1990.pdf" data-href="Newman 1990.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/newman-1990.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>
<br>Nieuwborg, Elie R. 1987. Retrograde woordenboek van de Nederlandse taal. Kluwer Technische Boeken. 1115 pages.

<br>(iirc I couldn't actually gain access to this?)


<br>Nieuwenhuis, Paul. 1985. Diminutives. University of Edinburgh, PhD thesis.&nbsp;(<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nieuwenhuis 1985.pdf" data-href="Nieuwenhuis 1985.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nieuwenhuis-1985.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Nurmio, Silva. 2023. Towards a typology of singulatives. Number Categories: Dynamics, Contact, Typology, 32, 155. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Nurmio 2023.pdf" data-href="Nurmio 2023.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/nurmio-2023.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Nurmio, Silva. Rahel T. Dires &amp; Matilda Carbo. Forthcoming. Singulatives: a typological database.<br>Nurmio, Silva. 202X. Herd mentality: how to talk about 'one' of animals in the Brittonic languages<br><br>Ott, Dennis. 2011. Diminutive-formation in German. The Journal of Comparative Germanic Linguistics, 14(1), 1-46.<br>Osselton, N. E. &amp; Hempelman R. 2003. The New Routledge Dutch-English Dictionary. Routledge, London.<br><br>Pharos<br>Pickl, Simon. (High) German. Oxford Research Encyclopedia of Linguistics. <a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780199384655.013.939" target="_blank">https://doi.org/10.1093/acrefore/9780199384655.013.939</a><br>Prinsloo, Anton. 2008. Annerlike Afrikaans: Woordeboek van Afrikaanse Kontreitaal. Protea Books.<br>Pradilla, Miquel Àngel. 1999. "El secessionisme lingüístic valencià", in: PRADILLA Miquel Àngel (1999) (ed.) La llengua catalana al tombant del mil·leni, Barcelona: Empúries, p. 153-202.<br><br><br>
<br>Robinson, Mairi. 1997. The Concise Scots Dictionary. Chambers

<br>paper iirc


<br>Rothstein 2017. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Rothstein 2017.pdf" data-href="Rothstein 2017.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/rothstein-2017.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>
<br>Ryding 2005

<br>paper iirc


<br><br>Schneider, Klaus. 2012. Diminutives in English. Walter de Gruyter.&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;&nbsp;<br>Scholze-Stubenrecht, W. &amp; Sykes, J.B. 1995. Oxford-Duden German-English English-German Dictionary. Oxford University Press.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://www.scottishcorpus.ac.uk/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.scottishcorpus.ac.uk/" target="_blank">Scottish Corpus of Texts &amp; Speech</a><br>Shetter, William Z. 1959. The Dutch Diminutive. Article in The Journal of English and Germanic Philology, 58(1), 75-90.<br>Shetter, William Z. and Inge Van der Cruysse-Van Antwerpen. 2002. Dutch: an essential grammar. Routledge.<br>
- (found newer edition; Shetter &amp; Ham 2007 = 9th)<br>Sifianou, Maria. 1992. The use of diminutives in expressing politeness: Modern Greek versus English. Journal of Pragmatics. Volume 17, issue 12. pp.155-173.<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://ivdnt.org/images/stories/producten/documentatie/cgn_website/doc_English/topics/index.htm" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://ivdnt.org/images/stories/producten/documentatie/cgn_website/doc_English/topics/index.htm" target="_blank">Spoken Dutch Corpus</a><br>&nbsp;Stein, Gabriele. 2013. A Usage Dictionary of English-German, German-English. De Gruyter-Mouton.<br>Stolz, Thomas. 2001. Singulative-Collective: Natural Morphology and stable classes in Welsh number inflexion on nouns. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Stolz 2001.pdf" data-href="Stolz 2001.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/stolz-2001.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><br>Taalportaal. Afrikaans › <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-1581327776365425" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-1581327776365425" target="_blank"><em></em></a>Preliminaries.<br> Taalportaal. Afrikaans › <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-15219838567096215" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-15219838567096215" target="_blank"><em></em></a>D__iminutive formation.<br>Taalportaal. Frisian › <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-13998813305497380#section_14z_p12_tq" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-13998813305497380#section_14z_p12_tq" target="_blank"><em></em></a>-DIM.<br>Taalportaal. Frisian › <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-14492293855521070#simpletable_4dl_rm2_mp" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-14492293855521070#simpletable_4dl_rm2_mp" target="_blank"><em></em></a>Gender.<br>Taalportaal. Frisian › <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-14085316936215013" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-14085316936215013" target="_blank"><em></em></a>Number.<br>Taalportaal. Dutch › <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-14419054123420388" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://taalportaal.org/taalportaal/topic/pid/topic-14419054123420388" target="_blank"><em></em></a>Nominal suffixation: diminutives.<br>Tiersma, Pieter Meijes. 1999. Frisian Reference Grammar. Fryske Akademy, 2nd ed.<br>Treis 2012. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Treis 2012.pdf" data-href="Treis 2012.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/treis-2012.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><br><br>Van Gelderen, Elly. 2010. An Introduction to the Grammar of English. Revised edition. John Benjamins Publishing Company.<br>
- (may have used an older edition originally, check)<br><br>Watts, Richard. 1999. "The ideology of dialect in Switzerland." Language ideological debates 2: 67-103.<br>Western Frisian Web 2013, Sketch Engine.<br>Wiese &amp; Maling. Grammatical coercion in Germanic languages. (Todo: integrate to my board + writing)<br>Wiltschko, Martina. 2006. Why should diminutives count. Organizing grammar. Linguistic studies in honor of Henk van Riemsdijk, 86, 669-679.<br>Wiltschko, Martina, and Olga Steriopolo. "Parameters of variation in the syntax of diminutives." Proceedings of the 2007 Canadian linguistics association annual conference. Vol. 1. Canadian Linguistic Association, 2007. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Wiltschko &amp; Steriopolo 2007.pdf" data-href="Wiltschko &amp; Steriopolo 2007.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/wiltschko-&amp;-steriopolo-2007.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>Witzlack-Makarevich 2019<br>Woolard 1998. Simultaneity and ambivalence as Strategies in Bilingualism<br><a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="https://ivdnt.org/woordenboeken/woordenboek-der-friese-taal/" rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://ivdnt.org/woordenboeken/woordenboek-der-friese-taal/" target="_blank">Woordenboek der Friese taal</a><br><br><br>Ylikoski, Jussi. 2022. Čalbmi čalmmis ja suoldnečalmmit suoidnečalmmis: Sámegielaid singulatiivvat. Nordlyd, 46(1), 299-307. (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Ylikoski 2022.pdf" data-href="Ylikoski 2022.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/ylikoski-2022.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br><br>
<br>Zeuss, Johann Kaspar. 1853. Grammatica Celtica.<br>
 
]]></description><link>draft/7.-references/7.-references.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/7. References/7. References.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:27:51 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[7.X Edited volumes]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>(Would be ideal to split referenced chapters, when not done already)<br>Acquaviva &amp; Daniel:<br>
<br>Fehri
<br>Garcia &amp; Hult 2018 Languages in Jewish communities, Past and Present<br>
<br>Beider 2018
<br>Handbook of Jewish Languages<br>
<br>Kahn 2015
<br>Irmengaard et al 1995<br>
<br>Jacobs 1995
<br>Joseph &amp; Janda 2003:<br>
<br>Heine 2003 (grammaticalization)
<br>Li et al 2014 (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Li et al 2014.pdf" data-href="Li et al 2014.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/edited-volumes/li-et-al-2014.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>
<br>Chierchia
<br>Massam 2012 (<a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="Massam 2012.pdf" data-href="Massam 2012.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/edited-volumes/massam-2012.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">link</a>)<br>
<br>Cheng 2012 (<a data-href="Cheng 2012.pdf" href="draft/7.-references/literature/cheng-2012.pdf" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">Cheng 2012.pdf</a>) = countability in chinese
<br>Matras, McMahon &amp; Vincent 2006. Linguistic Areas - Convergence in Historical and Typological Perspective<br>
<br>Anderson 2006
<br>Smith &amp; Veenstra 2001. Creolization and contact<br>
<br>Prince 'Yiddish as a contact language'

<br>I don't think I integrated that yet


<br>Val Olmen et al<br>
<br>Haspelmath 2018
]]></description><link>draft/7.-references/7.x-edited-volumes.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/7. References/7.X Edited volumes.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:36:33 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Appendix II. Identification of Scots]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>English VS Mixed VS Scots<br>
Woolard 1998<br>Scots features: Bergs 2005<br>List of documents identified as Scots, with features that support the identification]]></description><link>draft/8.-appendices/appendix-ii.-identification-of-scots.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/8. Appendices/Appendix II. Identification of Scots.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 12:35:02 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[index]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><a data-href="0.1 Cover" href="draft/0.-introduction/0.1-cover.html" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">0.1 Cover</a>]]></description><link>draft/index.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Draft/index.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 08:54:17 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[1. What]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>The idea is to: <br>
<br>centralize everything needed for the research project (sources, data, manuscript)
<br>make the manuscript a hypertext, rather than a linear document

<br>simplify navigation through hyperlinks
<br>make crossref far more transparent = less errors


<br>improve management of todos

<br>visualize:

<br>(1) recurring tasks: find sources, read, notes, write/edit
<br>(2) where to intervene

<br>"how/what" is more detailed at the location


<br>(1) and (2) get connected to represent task
<br>connect (2) nodes if they involve dependencies


<br>the point of this is: executive flexibility &amp; clarity


<br>It's a solution to:<br>
<br>clutter accumulation in documents (especially the draft)
<br>sprawl between different files, folders, apps
<br>uncertainty paralysis from todo not being adapted to cognitive needs of person doing the work
<br><br>
<br>Internal

<br>Link to other part of your draft (= 'signposting')
<br>"Check my crossref:" Link to exact page/excerpt where the info is from

<br>hardcore epistemic transparency


<br>(Link do not break when you edit titles of documents! YAY)


<br>External links to web pages
<br><br>
<br>Chapter = folder
<br>Further subdivisions of text = 1 page
<br><br>Data is stored in files, and at least two folders:<br>
<br>Primary data = with metadata and comments
<br>Secondary data = aggregation/manipulation of primary data<br>
... create links between primary &amp; secondary data -&gt; data stays situated without cluttering the aggregation/manipulation environment.<br>
... all of this can be dynamic, so that changes in primary data gets reflected in secondary data! (Overkill for my current project but very powerful for future, more complex/voluminous projects.)
<br><br>
<br>Folder with all(...ish) consulted publications

<br>(Absolute sicko mode would capture web pages as they appeared when you consulted them, too)


<br><br><br>
<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://victorianweb.org/neovictorian/gswift/htplan.html" target="_blank">https://victorianweb.org/neovictorian/gswift/htplan.html</a>
]]></description><link>hypertext-thesis/1.-what.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Hypertext thesis/1. What.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 16 Jan 2025 14:10:10 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[2. How]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Obsidian (other personal management system)<br>Recommended plugins<br>
<br>Interlinear Gloss

<br>(... not using it so far but will need it later)


<br>Kanban board
<br>PDF++: for annotating PDF directly in Obsidian. Will change the source file. (A bit slow so for heavy editing, do it outside Obsidian)
<br>Iconize: allows you to include icons in documents, next to document titles in lefthand bar, etc. (Eg use icons to mark status of a file)
<br>Remember cursor position
<br>Webpage HTML Export

<br>(Export doubles as an off-site backup! Host on Github -&gt; Github Pages. Your draft is now online!)
<br>


<br>Better Export Pdf

<br>for supervisor's reading + comments, and final submission of thesis


<br><br>Todo<br>
<br>streamline export

<br>export the pdfs
<br>improve appearance


<br>track what's changed between exports
]]></description><link>hypertext-thesis/2.-how.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Hypertext thesis/2. How.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Mon, 20 Jan 2025 11:24:29 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[3. ... why]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>to be HARDCORE<br>
<br>scalability of future research projects

<br>re: complexity, volume, collaboration with other people


<br>spot problems in crossref more easily

<br>both in terms of architecture (ref in text, ref in bib) and accuracy (of content)


<br>make it easier to jump in/out of work

<br>lower cognitive costs of starting work
<br>more resilient to disruptions


<br>reduce clutter in any given document

<br>less clutter = less distraction


<br>reduce sprawl between different files, folders, apps, whatever 

<br>less sprawl = less working memory-related executive blockages/slips


<br>ability to update the publication later

<br>(eg correct errors spotted laaate + amend 'forth.' articles that got published)


<br>dynamic -&gt; less work is needed for more/better sync between parts of the project (either: it's built-in, it's possible to automate, or it's easy to see where human intervention is needed) -&gt; focus more on thinking/writing than janitoring

<br>(... but lots of janitoring required up front if migrating from existing de-centralized draft. it's a front-loaded investment in time that seems worth it)


<br>lots of tools to adapt workflow/work environment to your cognitive specs

<br>essential if normal/usual way to do things work poorly for you (neurodivergence)
<br>(see: <a data-tooltip-position="top" aria-label="screenshot taskboard.png" data-href="screenshot taskboard.png" href="hypertext-thesis/screenshot-taskboard.png" class="internal-link" target="_self" rel="noopener nofollow">example of todo board</a> that enables me to (1) sort tasks by activity, to enable working in batches and reduce task switching, (2) see dependencies (&amp; hence eventual blockages), to simplify decisions re: what to do, in what order

<br>... this might look bonkers but more simple/linear todo lists were getting me nowhere)




<br><a rel="noopener nofollow" class="external-link" href="https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=au9377p59xs" target="_blank">https://www.youtube.com/watch?v=au9377p59xs</a><br>
HARDCORRRRE]]></description><link>hypertext-thesis/3.-...-why.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Hypertext thesis/3. ... why.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:45:24 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Finding sources for linguistic research]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>less legal options that i am not explicitly endorsing<br>
<br>
your university library

<br>
other libraries in your city/country maybe (inter-library loan)

<br>
google scholar (articles)

<br>
sci-hub (articles post 2000-ish; search w DOI)

<br>
library genesis (books)

<br>
hh (dictionaries &amp; grammars galore)

<br>
regular old google

<br>
academia.edu

<br>
researchgate

<br>
google books (consult books)

<br>
internet library (consult OLD books)

<br>(inhale 300 years' worth of dust for a truly immersive experience)


<br>
last resort once you've checked everywhere:

<br>friends' university libraries
<br>kindness of strangers via resource sharing sites/groups...
<br>(perhaps give up)


]]></description><link>hypertext-thesis/finding-sources-for-linguistic-research.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Hypertext thesis/Finding sources for linguistic research.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:38:43 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[PDF export]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br>Being able to export draft in PDF matters for:<br>
<br>Comments from supervisor
<br>Tracking page count
<br>Final submission of thesis
<br>Plugin 'Better Export PDF' allows to export content of a folder in a single PDF<br>
<br>(Interacts oddly with plugin Iconize, messing up the order -&gt; remove icons to track note status when exporting)
<br>All hyperlinks become static text
<br>Resulting text format generally looks OK

<br>(have a quick look at the preview when exporting)
<br>(will want to make it look more polished for final submission)


<br>PDF export requires solving: how to integrate supervisor's comments (low clutter when writing + full content visible when exporting)<br>
<br>Current solution: indented collapsible text

<br>in italics + paragraph so I can quickly spot it as paratext, not text
<br>comment relates to whatever is above it
<br>
<br>(Comment function native to Obsidian '%% ... %%' = used to track technical bits that are irrelevant to my supervisor)


]]></description><link>hypertext-thesis/pdf-export.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Hypertext thesis/PDF export.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Thu, 23 Jan 2025 11:27:40 GMT</pubDate></item><item><title><![CDATA[Adding sources]]></title><description><![CDATA[ 
 <br><br>Find source online<br>
Skim for relevance<br>
Download, rename file<br>
<br>(Get/ask someone to get physical copy, then digitize, return)<br>
Place in vault folder<br>
Add to References, link<br>
Add note to relevant paragraph
<br><br>Add comment where it belongs in my draft<br>
Update my task board]]></description><link>hypertext-thesis/workflow.html</link><guid isPermaLink="false">Hypertext thesis/Workflow.md</guid><dc:creator><![CDATA[Matilda Carbo]]></dc:creator><pubDate>Fri, 17 Jan 2025 12:17:21 GMT</pubDate></item></channel></rss>